<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French intrigues discovered with the methods and arts to retrench the potency of France by land and sea and to confine that monarch within his antient dominions and territories : humbly submitted to the consideration of the princes and states of Europe, especially of England / written in a letter from a person of quality abroad to his corrsepondent here.</title>
            <author>Person of quality abroad.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2185</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9404</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13743832</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13743832</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101686</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40459)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101686)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 454:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The French intrigues discovered with the methods and arts to retrench the potency of France by land and sea and to confine that monarch within his antient dominions and territories : humbly submitted to the consideration of the princes and states of Europe, especially of England / written in a letter from a person of quality abroad to his corrsepondent here.</title>
                  <author>Person of quality abroad.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101686:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101686:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE French Intrigues DISCOVERED. With the Methods and Arts TO Retrench the Potency OF FRANCE BY LAND and SEA, And to Confine that MONARCH Within his Antient DOMINIONS and TERRITORIES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Humbly ſubmitted to the Conſideration of the PRINCES and STATES of</hi> EUROPE, <hi>eſpecially of</hi> ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Written in a LETTER From a Perſon of Quality abroad, to his Correſpondent here.</p>
            <q>Nulla potentia ſcelere quaeſita, est diuturna.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:101686:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101686:2"/>
            <head>THE French Intrigues DISCOVERED, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN obedience to your Commands, I have ſoberly conſidered your learned Diſcourſe; wherein are ſuch excellent Prudentials of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſuch grave <hi>Aphoriſms</hi> of State, and the whole compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſo great judgment, that it makes me think the Opinion of the equality of Souls, to be a Paradox: Yet I muſt beg your pardon, if I cannot obtain ſo much favour of my Reaſon, as to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with you, that in this Juncture of Affairs in <hi>Europe,</hi> it's <hi>England</hi>'s <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> to ſtand Neutral.</p>
            <p>When Neighbour-<hi>Princes</hi> are at difference, and their Forces not great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unequal, and no fear of any Parties aggrandizing it ſelf, it may be prudence:</p>
            <p>But when <hi>Kingdoms</hi> are tottering, <hi>Nation</hi> reeling againſt <hi>Nation,</hi> and <hi>France</hi> endeavouring to ſet up an <hi>Empire</hi> over the <hi>Emperour</hi> himſelf, and by the power of <hi>Arms</hi> reducing <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> under an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Dominion</hi> (as it's evident to be the <hi>French</hi> Deſigne;) then I take it, for <hi>England</hi> to be an idle Spectator and to ſit ſtill, is the greateſt <hi>Soloeciſm</hi> in point of State: For that <hi>Prince</hi> which ſtands Neutral, and ſuffers his weaker Neighbours to be ſubdued, (except his ſtrength doth over-bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance the Victors) doth but expoſe himſelf to danger, and his own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions to the mercie of the Conqueror.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theramenes</hi> thought it a great inſtance of prudence, during the <hi>Pelopon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſian</hi> War, and the troubles of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> to keep himſelf quiet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking part with the one or with the other; but in the end was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted by all, his Dominions made a Prey, and his Life a Sacrifice to the prevailing Powers.</p>
            <p>Certainly, Sir, nothing can be more becoming the wiſdom of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Prince,</hi> than to be watchful that the <hi>States</hi> about him ſhould not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greaten themſelves by acceſs of Dominions, by ruining of Confederates, blocking up of Trade, or by the like means.</p>
            <p>Hence it was that <hi>Sextus Quintus</hi> being jealous of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Greatneſs, and that his deſigne was of aggrandizing himſelf, with great efficacy ſtirred up the <hi>Crown of France</hi> to aſſiſt and defend the <hi>States of Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for this reaſon of State, <hi>Pope Julius</hi> the <hi>ſecond, Maximilian</hi> the <hi>Emperour, Lewis</hi> the <hi>twelfth</hi> of <hi>France, Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Aragon,</hi> and other <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States, An. Dom.</hi> 1508. at <hi>Cambray,</hi> entred into a League a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101686:3"/>the <hi>Venetians;</hi> yet ſo as the Confederates had a perpetual Eye one upon the other, that none of them ſhould over top.</p>
            <p>And the beſt Guard which the <hi>Italian Princes</hi> have, is the reciprocal fear which the one of them hath of the other.</p>
            <p>The wiſeſt <hi>Princes</hi> have ever been in this point very jealous, (and the more jealous, the leſs they have been deceived;) for then are <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>States</hi> moſt ſafe, when their Neighbouring Forces are not greatly ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to their own Strength.</p>
            <p>And it's prudence in a <hi>Prince,</hi> as well to contain his beſt Friends within a moderate Greatneſs, as to weaken and depreſs his moſt potent Enemies.</p>
            <p>The ſafety of <hi>Princes</hi> conſiſts in the equal counterpoiſe of Power; for Power is never ſafe when it groweth bold and doth exceed.</p>
            <p>And therefore it was great weakneſs and overſight in the Neighbouring <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> to the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſuffer it to grow to that magnitude of Reputation and Power, that when forty <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> being jealous of its Power, with united Forces did endeavour to reduce it, they were all ſubdued; and their Conſpiracies did much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the enlarging ber Dominions: for by ſeeking to ſuppreſs <hi>Rome,</hi> they made them not onely provide for their own defence, but alſo gave them the means how they might, with more Force, better advice, and greater Power offend them.</p>
            <p>It hath been looked upon as a great imprudence in <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth of <hi>France,</hi> after he had gotten <hi>Millain,</hi> to give Aid to <hi>Pope Alexander</hi> to ſeize upon <hi>Romagnia;</hi> who thereby became ſo powerful, that he would have made himſelf Lord of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> if <hi>Lewis</hi> had not with his Army made a deſcent into <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Neighbouring <hi>Princes</hi> to the Signiory of <hi>Geneva</hi> would not ſuffer it (though but a palm of ground) to fall into the hands of the <hi>Duke of Savoy,</hi> or of any other Potentate of more ſtrength than himſelf; inſomuch that when he beſieged it <hi>An.</hi> 1589. <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>State of Venice,</hi> and <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> aided them. And at another time, when the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>French King,</hi> the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> had deſignes upon it, the <hi>Emperour</hi> offered them aſſiſtance both of men and money; and ſometimes the <hi>Duke of Savoy</hi> hath aſſiſted them againſt the others.</p>
            <p>So watchful were <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> in thoſe times, that none of them could enlarge their Dominions, thereby to become troubleſom or formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable to their Neighbours. <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> were the <hi>Scales</hi> of the great <hi>Ballance</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> and <hi>England</hi> was then the <hi>Beam</hi> of that <hi>Ballance,</hi> which kept it in an even <hi>Counterpoiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let me tell you, Sir, <hi>England,</hi> by obſerving this fundamental <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime</hi> of their State, and by contributing Aid to one Party, hath ever riſen in Honour and Reputation; and moſt commonly hath kept both Parties at their Devotion, and in Dependancy, the one in hopes of Succors from them, the other for fear of their giving Aſſiſtance againſt them.</p>
            <p>And in caſe <hi>England</hi> ſhould not take any Party, yet in prudence a <hi>Fleet</hi> muſt be <hi>equipped, Souldiers raiſed,</hi> an <hi>Army maintained,</hi> and all this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence and Charge without any Fruit or Glory; otherwiſe the <hi>Scene</hi> of the War may be turned upon you, and the Ambition of the Victor may erect his Trophies, and extend his Triumphs into <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas by giving Aid unto one Party, you will maintain a Spring and Seminary of brave men at the expence of others, (which will make you conſiderable to your Neighbours.) And in caſe of an Accommodation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101686:3"/>or Peace, you ſhall be ſure therein to be comprized; which will be your Safety; Otherwiſe you will remain friendleſs, expoſed to the charity of the Conqueror, and to the ſcorn and contempt of the Conquered; who upon all occaſions will meditate revenge againſt you for not giving them your Aid, and it may be that both Parties with united Forces may attempt againſt you.</p>
            <p>However, that <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>State</hi> which will ſtand for a <hi>Cypher,</hi> when in prudence he is obliged to arm, ſhall with <hi>Servilius</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> pleaſe neither ſide; of whom the Hiſtorian obſerveth, that <hi>P. Servilius medium ſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo, nec Plebis vitavit odium, nec apud Patres gratiam inivit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth</hi> (amongſt ſeveral other Princes) underſtood this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime of <hi>England</hi> ſo well, that he aſſumed unto himſelf this Motto, <hi>Cui adhaereo, praeest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes he would make <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Fiſth</hi> weigh down, ſometimes <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>Firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1522. at <hi>Cambray</hi> he ſettled all <hi>Europe</hi> in quiet (when it was much turmoiled) and <hi>Italy</hi> in ſecurity; therefore he was ſtiled, <hi>Protector of the Clementine League:</hi> the Inſtrument whereof doth ſtill remain in the Treaſury at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ſealed with gold.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Clement</hi> the <hi>Seventh</hi> being cooped up by <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Fifth</hi> in the Caſtle of St. <hi>Angelo,</hi> was freed by the means of <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and therefore by the whole Conſiſtory of <hi>Rome,</hi> he was called <hi>Liberator Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Fifth,</hi> An. 1521. was by him made <hi>Emperour,</hi> as he doth acknowledge in two Letters to <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and indeed he was the great Arbitrator of all the Aſſairs of <hi>Europe</hi> in his time.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth</hi> was ſo much celebrated for keeping the ballance in <hi>aequilibrio,</hi> what Glory and Renown will his now <hi>Sacred Majeſty</hi> of <hi>Great Britain</hi> have, by putting a Batricado to the Ambition of the <hi>French Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> and reintegrating all <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> in their ancient Liberties and juſt Rights, and ſetling the Peace of all <hi>Europe</hi> upon a ſolid Baſis? which onely by his Wiſdom and Power is to be effected.</p>
            <p>An Act certainly ſo full of Grandeur, that it will tread upon the grave of Hiſtory, bury Monuments, ſee the Worlds funeral, Time laid in the duſt, and ſtand up with Eternity.</p>
            <p>The glory of Soveraignty conſiſts not in a Chair of State, but in ſuch Acts as are well-becoming a <hi>Prince.</hi> Private men may direct their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels to ſuch things as they think may be proſitable to them, but the Actions of <hi>Princes</hi> muſt tend to Grandeur, and the attaining of Honour and Fame.</p>
            <p>For want of due obſervation of this prime and <hi>Alphabetical Maxime</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>French King</hi> of late hath riſen up to that Greatneſs, and is arrived to that <hi>Pyramid</hi> of Grandeur, that <hi>Europe</hi> begins to bow to his Power.</p>
            <p>Univerſal Empire was firſt attempted by <hi>Charles,</hi> the <hi>Fifth,</hi> deſigned by <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> but will be effected (if not timely prevented) by <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Potent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how great a Progreſs he hath made towards ſo vaſt a Deſigne, it well becomes your great Judgment to conſider.</p>
            <p>He hath gotten <hi>Briſac</hi> and <hi>Friburg,</hi> to enter <hi>Germany;</hi> the <hi>French Comte,</hi> to a we the <hi>Switzers; Pignoral,</hi> to enter <hi>Italy; Perpignan,</hi> to enter <hi>Spain;</hi> and almoſt all <hi>Flanders,</hi> to enter <hi>England.</hi> Beſides, he hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patronized himſelf of the Countries of <hi>Rouſillon</hi> and <hi>Catalonia,</hi> the <hi>Dutchies</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101686:4"/>of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Barr, Alſatia, Burgundy;</hi> The <hi>French Comte,</hi> all the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> are in his Talons, and he hath a hovering poſſeſſion of the remainder, as a Hobby hath over a Lark.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Italian</hi> Gariſon in <hi>Avignion</hi> is caſheer'd, and he is Maſter of that place, though it was part of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s poſſeſſion three hundred years.</p>
            <p>The Gariſon of Foreign Souldiers which were in <hi>Orange,</hi> is diſmiſſed, and the Caſtle is diſmantled which was in the bowels of one of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces.</p>
            <p>What will he not be able to compaſs againſt the reſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> when he hath gotten the Acceſſion of <hi>Germany</hi> and all the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> to that already too boundleſs Power, by which he hath inſlaved his own people, and ſubjected them to an abſolute Vaſſalage?</p>
            <p>Can <hi>England</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Europe</hi> expect better terms than he hath given to his own Subjects? 'Tis well if he allow them Canvas and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
            <p>By Sea he is become ſo potent, that I queſtion if he were but furniſhed with Mariners and experienced Commanders ſuitable to the goodneſs of his Ships, if he might not contraſt the power of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and make the Sea between <hi>Callis</hi> and <hi>Dover</hi> as a Ferry to paſs over what Armies he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the beginning of the year 1665. he was not able to put to Sea twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ships of War; now he hath two hundred and upwards, and many larger than moſt in <hi>Europe,</hi> and is every day building more. Is it not then neceſſary for <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands,</hi> and all <hi>Europe,</hi> to look about them, and to ſecure their Necks againſt the Yoke of Slavery with which he threatens them? If ſome timely Expedient be not applied, from this Naval Power of <hi>France</hi> the deſtruction of <hi>Europe</hi> may take its date before we be much older.</p>
            <p>It will much concern <hi>England</hi> in point of Intereſt, to conſider if <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Scheme of their deſignes, may not be looked upon as a Country which may procure <hi>France</hi> the abſolute dominion of the Sea, of Trade, and the Conqueſt of the <hi>Weſt Indies;</hi> which have been their antient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p>For he being ſo potent at Sea, they may from <hi>Brest</hi> tranſmit an Army into <hi>Ireland</hi> (they having many of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation in their ſervice, and thoſe diſcontented) if they ſhould ſeize upon <hi>Kingsale</hi> or <hi>Waterford,</hi> and keep a good Squadron of Ships there, (which they may do, having ſuch numbers of Men of War). And though it ſhould not prove the loſs of that Nation, yet it would obſtruct and debar all Trade upon thoſe Seas: And if you have any Ship paſs there, it muſt be by their favour, and paying what Tribute they pleaſe to impoſe.</p>
            <p>Be aſſured, Sir, the <hi>French Cabal</hi> have ſome notable Deſigne againſt <hi>England,</hi> either to engage you in a Civil War by diſſeminating of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions amongſt you, thereby to put a diſability upon his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> to give any Aſſiſtance, or contribute any Aid to the relief of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands,</hi> in caſe by his Arms he ſhould attack them, as without diſpute he will, in caſe there be not a ſtop put to his Career.</p>
            <p>Or peradventure the <hi>French King</hi> (if the <hi>Capricio</hi> ſhall take him) may by his Arms give diſturbance to <hi>England</hi> it ſelf: For he cannot think it ſafe to proceed in his Conqueſt on the Continent, whiles he hath ſo dangerous an Enemy as <hi>England</hi> at his reer. He well knows the Courage and Gallantry of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and your <hi>Talbots</hi> and <hi>Bedfords</hi> are not by them forgotten.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101686:4"/>They are ſetting up an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> of <hi>Commerce,</hi> and to make <hi>France</hi> the <hi>Staple</hi> of Trade; and to that purpoſe do labour to get what Ports they can into their power.</p>
            <p>After the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Peace, they immediately entred into a League Offenſive and Defenſive with <hi>Portugal,</hi> though contrary to the Faith of that Treaty; and all the Harbours and Ports which the <hi>Portugal</hi> ſhould take in <hi>Spain,</hi> either upon the one or other Sea, were to be put into the power of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No ſooner was <hi>Dunkirk</hi> in the <hi>French King</hi>'s hands, but he made it a free Port. And that he might want no Seamen of his own, he hath by all imaginable Encouragements, eſtabliſhed a mighty Navigation in <hi>France,</hi> and thereby will lay the foundation of a greater Empire than ever was in <hi>Charlemain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>one</hi> trading Ship twenty years ſince, there are now <hi>forty.</hi> For this purpoſe he hath propagated the Fiſhery in <hi>Newfound Land</hi> (which is the <hi>Propriety</hi> of the Crown of <hi>England</hi>) and where they formerly (till now of late) never fiſhed but by Licenſe, and paying a Tribute to the Kings of <hi>England;</hi> and beſides, hath yearly educated ſupernumerary Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men on board the French Trading-Ships at his own charges.</p>
            <p>He hath engaged moſt of his Nobility in the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West Indian</hi> Trades; and the better to encourage them, hath granted many Priviledges to them.</p>
            <p>And without doubt, by reaſon of his great preparations by Sea, he hath ſome great Deſigne in projection. If he ſhall propoſe to make himſelf Maſter of the <hi>Indies,</hi> I do not ſee how he can fail in his Attempts, if <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> be not more watchful.</p>
            <p>By an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Privy Council (which is the now ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Law of that Kingdom) all the Officers and Commanders in the <hi>Iſlands</hi> of <hi>America,</hi> are ſtrictly enjoyned and required to ſecure to the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King the Soveraignty of thoſe Seas; and the <hi>French</hi> in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, have much interrupted the Trade there, and have proved very vexatious.</p>
            <p>And having erected the <hi>East India</hi> Trade, he hath attempted to get foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in divers places in the <hi>East Indies:</hi> What his ſucceſs may be, time will ſhew.</p>
            <p>But if he ſhould unite the <hi>Dutch</hi> Trade and Strengths in thoſe parts to himſelf, by an Union of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> and their Navigation to his Empire, (as he will, if ſome timely Aſſiſtance be not given by <hi>England</hi>) how the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Factories there will then preſerve themſelves from Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or utter Extirpation, it doth well become <hi>England</hi> to conſider: For <hi>France</hi> deſignes to engroſs the Trade of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by their irregular courſe of Trade, they will exhauſt all <hi>Europe</hi> of their Money. I have heard that <hi>England</hi> loſeth yearly by the <hi>French</hi> Trade 1500000 <hi>l. ſterling;</hi> and I am ſure they draw out of the <hi>Northern</hi> Regions of <hi>Europe,</hi> for Wines, 25 <hi>Millions</hi> of <hi>Florens;</hi> for Salt 10 <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions</hi> of <hi>Florens;</hi> for Brandy 5 <hi>Millions;</hi> for Wines, Brandy, and Salt, they yearly exhauſt from thence 40 <hi>Millions</hi> of <hi>Florens;</hi> for Silks, Stuffs, Toys, and Fripparies, they ſpirit out of thoſe Countries yearly 40 <hi>Millions</hi> of <hi>Florens:</hi> and there is not imported into <hi>France</hi> of the Commodities of all the North ſo many as do amount unto 15 <hi>Millions</hi> of <hi>Florens.</hi> So that <hi>France</hi> doth yearly drain out of the Northern Regions of <hi>Europe</hi> 65 <hi>Millions</hi> of <hi>Florens.</hi> And what great and prodigious ſums of money he draweth from the reſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> muſt be left to ſober men to conſider.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101686:5"/>But no Foreign Commodities can be imported into <hi>France,</hi> but they are clog'd and incumbred with ſuch great Duties and Cuſtoms, that the return made thereof to the Merchant is without any profit.</p>
            <p>His Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Majeſty having for his Royal Revenue <hi>Sixty Millions</hi> of <hi>Florens</hi> yearly, and <hi>France</hi> being inriched yearly as aboveſaid, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able by his ſupream power, without any check or controul, to impoſe what Taxes he pleaſes; he hath laid ſuch an inexhauſtible <hi>Fond</hi> of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to carry on his deſignes to the Oppreſſion of all <hi>Europe,</hi> that he can rarely be diſappointed or fail in any: He can ſupport his Armies, when other Princes are enforced to beg for Peace becauſe their Treaſures are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted.</p>
            <p>He, after many years War, can engage in a new War; and upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, by reaſon of his Treaſure, have Inſtruments to execute his Projects.</p>
            <p>By this he purchaſes the aſſiſtance of Foreign <hi>Princes,</hi> and endears their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> opens their <hi>Cabinets,</hi> engageth true and cloſe Correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and poyſons their Councils. By this he can paſs unſeen through Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers and Guards into Cities and Forts, and can ſurprize them, without te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious hazards of Guards. And many contemplative men think that he hath gained more Territories and Dominions by his <hi>Piſtols,</hi> than by his <hi>Sword</hi> and <hi>Cannon:</hi> So that the <hi>Serpent</hi> is more ſerviceable to them than the <hi>Dragon</hi> as acting with leſs noiſe and greater execution. Ambition is the Compaſs whereby they ſail, and Univerſal Dominion the Port where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto their courſe is directed; and as their Ambition hath no <hi>Horizon,</hi> ſo their Deſignes have no <hi>Latitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>fifth</hi> his Motto, <hi>Plus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltra,</hi> and his Son <hi>Philip</hi>'s, <hi>Non ſufficit Orbis,</hi> diſcovered their vaſt Ambition: And doth not that of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>eleventh, Immenſi tremor Oceani,</hi> and that of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>fourteenth, Solus contra Omnes,</hi> manifeſt the Deſignes of <hi>France?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, if there be not a Retrenchment of the ſpreading and ambitious Deſignes of <hi>France,</hi> I am ſometimes of the opinion, that the Moſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> King may ere long take upon him that jolly humour of the great <hi>Cham</hi> of <hi>Tartary;</hi> who when he hath dined, commands his Trumpeters to ſound, and make proclamation that now all other Kings and Princes may ſit down to dinner.</p>
            <p>It will be worth the while, that all <hi>Europe</hi> may be ſatisfied of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the <hi>French Cabal,</hi> to conſider the candor and integrity of their Actions for ſome years laſt paſt; and whether they may expect better Principles and Methods from them for the future, than they have hitherto had. The firſt Eſſay of their Ingenuity and Honeſty, was in their beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and carriage in the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty, and their performance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>By the Endeavours of the <hi>Queen-Mother</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> a Peace being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted between the two Crowns of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> with a Marriage between the <hi>French King</hi> and the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain;</hi> the whole Treaty was founded upon two conſiderable points: The one was the forſaking of <hi>Portugal;</hi> the other a Renunciation of the <hi>Infanta</hi> (ratified by the <hi>French King</hi>) of all her preſent or future pretences, titles, or claims what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever to the Spaniſh Monarchy and Dominions thereof; which if not granted, the great work of the Match had never taken effect. As to the firſt, the <hi>French King</hi> did promiſe and oblige himſelf upon his <hi>Honour,</hi> and upon the <hi>Faith</hi> of a King, not to give at preſent or for the future, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in common, nor to any perſon or perſons thereof in particular, any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101686:5"/>help or aſſiſtance, neither publick nor ſeeret, directly or indirectly, of Men, Munition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> under any pretence whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Yet the Peace was no ſooner made, but they ſent them Supplies of Men, Arms, and Money; and a while after, notwithſtanding their former Treaty with <hi>Spain</hi> in the view of the whole world, they entred into an <hi>Offenſive</hi> League with that Kingdom againſt all their Enemies.</p>
            <p>The other was the Renunciation aforementioned: And as to this, the <hi>French King,</hi> after the death of the late <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> claimed (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſaid Renunciation) a great part of the <hi>Spaniſh Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> as being devolved to him in the Right of his Wife; and to take poſſeſſion thereof, invaded the Country contrary to his Engagements, and ſo deſtructive to the Eſſence of the Treaty, with a powerful Army. The Marquiſs <hi>de la Fuente</hi> extraordinary Embaſſadour from <hi>Spain,</hi> being upon his return into <hi>Spain,</hi> upon the death of the late King his Maſter, his Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Majeſty did with all poſſible Aſſeverations engage his <hi>Faith</hi> and his <hi>Royal Vow,</hi> That he would religiouſly obſerve and keep the Peace, and continue a faithful Friendſhip both to the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> and to her <hi>Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Ambrun,</hi> after the French Army was already in the Field, and had poſſeſſed <hi>Charleroy,</hi> ſome ſive days before the News of it came to <hi>Madrid,</hi> did <hi>in verbo Sacerdotis,</hi> and upon all that is moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, proteſt and vow to the <hi>Queen,</hi> That his <hi>Maſter</hi> intended nothing leſs than what was reported of him, and would not break with the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> or invade his Dominions; as long as he was under age.</p>
            <p>Theſe Circumſtances are more ſurprizing than the Breach it ſelf. But the March of the French Army, and the Hoſtility they committed, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo little with their Vows and Promiſes, and the ſame being complained of, they anſwered, It was no Breach; and that they onely came fairly and in a friendly manner to take poſſeſſion of what belonged to them.</p>
            <p>This War, or as the <hi>French</hi> term it, a Friendly poſſeſſing of their own, ended by a Treaty at <hi>Aix;</hi> after which, contrary to the <hi>faith</hi> of that <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> they firſt diſmantled the ſtrong places and holds of the <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> carried away all Munition out of the Country; and notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſame Treaty at <hi>Aix,</hi> they exacted great Contributions from the <hi>Dutchies</hi> of <hi>Limburg</hi> and <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> and laid a new Claim to ſome Towns as important as any of thoſe granted to them by the Peace, and confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated the Eſtates of the Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> that would not forſwear their Allegiance. If theſe Infractions, and many more, are not ſufficient to awaken <hi>England</hi> and all <hi>Europe,</hi> I know not what will.</p>
            <p>Since the Treaty at <hi>Nimmeguen,</hi> ſuch have been the actings of the <hi>French Miniſters,</hi> ſuch Contraventions thereof, ſuch horrid Injuſtice hath been committed and executed upon the Subjects of his <hi>Catholick</hi> Majeſty in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> and elſe where, notwithſtanding the great Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories granted to the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian King</hi> by that fatal and deſtructive Peace (which all <hi>Europe</hi> may have time enough to repent and lament) that no King in the world can in juſtice own or give any countenance thereunto. Certainly there men act as if great ſins would merit Heaven by an <hi>Antiperiſtaſis.</hi> Thus they have dealt with <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us ſee how other <hi>Princes</hi> have fared with them.</p>
            <p>We'll begin with the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who by the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty was to be reſtored to his <hi>Dutchie</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> with all the places and Towns which he had poſſeſſed in the <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> of <hi>Metz, Toul,</hi> and <hi>Verdun;</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101686:6"/>but contrary to the Treaty, the <hi>French</hi> King refuſed to reſtore it, and to this day doth detain it; and ordered one of his Generals to ſeize his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and to bring him either dead or alive, (as it's the uſual practice of all Uſurpers to deſtroy thoſe they have diſpoſſeſſed and injured): and it was very near being effected.</p>
            <p>A new way of dealing with a Soveraign Prince, not yet known in theſe parts of the world, and which gives ſome hopes to <hi>Europe</hi> of ſeeing ere long the <hi>West</hi> governed by <hi>Baſhaws,</hi> as well as the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> None but an <hi>Univerſal Monarch</hi> can pretend to a Right of diſplacing <hi>Princes,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing both of their Lives and Territories: And therefore nothing could deſerve a higher Reſentment, nor a more vigorous Oppoſition from all the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kingdom of <hi>Poland</hi> comes next; which hath lain a bleeding ever ſince they had a <hi>French Queen,</hi> and which is at this inſtant in imminent danger of being conquered by the <hi>Turks,</hi> through the means of the <hi>French Cabal,</hi> who have called into the Kingdom the Enemy of the Chriſtian name, meerly becauſe they could not have a King either of <hi>French Bloud</hi> or of <hi>French Interest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Newburg</hi> was not better uſed, whom they cauſed to engage the greateſt part of his Eſtate almoſt beyond redemption, in hopes of the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Crown which they had promiſed to raiſe him to, by the help of a ſtrong Party they had made in that Kingdom: Yet underhand, contrary both to their Treaties (as well with the <hi>Elector</hi> of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> as with himſelf) and to their reiterated Promiſes and Vows, both by word of mouth and in writing, they did by their Creatures and Agents oppoſe the ſaid <hi>Duke</hi>'s pretenſion, and endeavoured with all induſtry to have the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Conde</hi> preferred before all other Competitors.</p>
            <p>Nothing certainly can be a greater inſtance of the perfidiouſneſs and treachery of the <hi>French Miniſters,</hi> and how little faith or credit is to be given to any of their Promiſes or Vows. If there were no other inſtance thereof, this alone were ſufficient to alarm the World to be careful and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed how they put any truſt in them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Emperour</hi> hath as little reaſon to thank them; for at the very time when the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King ſent his Forces to joyn with his Army a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> they began to ſettle a Correſpondence with the Counts <hi>Serini, Franchipani, Nadaſty,</hi> and <hi>Toffenback;</hi> from whence that ſo-well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Conſpiracy hath ſince broken out, as it hath been made apparent by the Depoſitions and Confeſſions of ſome of the Accomplices, who had been inſtrumental in carrying both Money and Letters from the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters at <hi>Vienna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the Confuſions, Diſtempers, and Wars in <hi>Hungary,</hi> have been raiſed and continued by the Practices and Intrigues of <hi>France.</hi> And they have given diſturbance to all <hi>Germany</hi> by their private Treaties and Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies with ſeveral <hi>Princes,</hi> contrary to the Treaty at <hi>Munſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which may be added, That one of the greateſt Motives of bringing the <hi>Turks</hi> into <hi>Poland,</hi> was the Marriage of the <hi>Empreſs</hi>'s <hi>Siſter</hi> with their <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet it muſt be owned, that the <hi>French</hi> ſeem to have repented their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Intrigues and <hi>caballing</hi> in that Kingdom: For when they ſaw the <hi>Emperour</hi> preparing in earneſt to aſſiſt the <hi>Dutch</hi> (in the late Wars they made againſt them) to work him from that deſigne, and to engage him (if it had been poſſible) not to concern himſelf or take part in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101686:6"/>Quarrel; they very fairly offered him to put into his hands and deliver him all the original Letters they had from their Creatures and Friends in <hi>Poland,</hi> to the end both his <hi>Imperial Majeſty</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Poland</hi> his Brother might take what courſe they thought fit with thoſe <hi>Rebels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A fair warning to all thoſe that prefer French Money before their Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and the true Intereſt of their Country.</p>
            <p>Nay, I doubt the <hi>Swedes,</hi> their good friends, have not always been pleaſed with them; and they cannot to this day forget, that about eighteen years ſince, having made a Treaty with the <hi>French,</hi> whereby they were to receive by way of gratuity or penſion ſixteen hundred thouſand Crowns, the <hi>French</hi> (upon ſecond thoughts) finding their Treaty with <hi>Sweden</hi> of little uſe to them, refuſed to ratifie it; and ſent their Monſieur <hi>de Trelon,</hi> who without more words told them in ſhort, That the King his Maſter declared it to be void. A ſine Court-ſtile for one Prince to uſe to another I and a ſhort Majeſtick way of reſcinding all Treaties.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſtupendious paſſages, and will be no more credited by Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, than we do what is ſaid of King <hi>Arthur</hi>'s round Table.</p>
            <p>It's needleſs to tell you, how they have obſerved their Treaties with <hi>Holland;</hi> for all <hi>Europe</hi> hath taken notice of it.</p>
            <p>They are in continual acqueſts of Dominion by <hi>force</hi> or <hi>fraud;</hi> and what they get by <hi>fraud,</hi> they keep by <hi>force:</hi> for the Sword, with them, is ever better than half the Title to any Dominion.</p>
            <p>They do not onely purſue, but commonly wound their Adverſary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they declare him ſuch, or give him leiſure to draw. They firſt invade a Princes Territories, and after ſet up their Title and Cauſe of War. They are not concerned, that all the world obſerve their pretence to be falſe and trifling, vain and unjuſt, warranted by no other reaſon than that of abſolute and unbounded Will, which are the foundation and concluſion of all the Actions (of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian King</hi>) and Wars abroad, as well as of his Laws and Edicts at home, expreſſed in theſe imperious words, <hi>Tel est Noſtre Plaiſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's a prime <hi>Maxime</hi> of the <hi>French Cabal,</hi> That that Prince which wars for his Glory, and avows Power to be the Rule, and Strength the Law of Juſtice, may without Right enter upon any Princes Dominions, and may in Honour and Juſtice detain them, ſo they be of conveniency to him to keep them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dukes</hi> of <hi>Lorrain, Deux-ponts,</hi> and <hi>Mewthelward,</hi> and the <hi>ten free Towns</hi> in <hi>Alſatia,</hi> ſufficiently prove the truth thereof.</p>
            <p>They have erected at <hi>Metz,</hi> a Court where his Moſt <hi>Chriſtian Majeſty,</hi> as <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Party,</hi> cites the moſt <hi>August</hi> and Illuſtrious Houſes of the Empire, (which he hath nothing to do withal) to make their appearance, and to give him an account by what Right they poſſeſs that which their Predeceſſors have for three or four hundred years peaceably enjoyed.</p>
            <p>His pretentions are to the greateſt part of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the whole <hi>Dukedom</hi> of <hi>Deux-ponts,</hi> and the beſt part of <hi>Alſatia</hi> as far as <hi>Lauterburg.</hi> Theſe, as ancient Dependencies of the <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> of <hi>Metz, Toul,</hi> and <hi>Verdun,</hi> and <hi>Therſow,</hi> muſt be reunited to that Crown, becauſe they are of conveniency for him. By this all Kings, Princes, and States, may ſee what they are to expect, if they come within the <hi>deſpotical</hi> power of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All Princes and States which may give them any jealouſie, they keep employed, and deſigne to depreſs all Powers which are capable of obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Torrent of their Ambition. All <hi>Europe</hi> is ſenſible thereof, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101686:7"/>their grief: They have engaged the <hi>Swedes</hi> to embroil the <hi>Empire;</hi> which they did to the loſs of all their Territories and Dominions in <hi>Germany:</hi> And they brought the <hi>Turks</hi> upon the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> whereby the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Army in <hi>Livonia,</hi> was let looſe upon the <hi>Confederate</hi> Princes.</p>
            <p>They worked the <hi>Meſſineſſes</hi> to form a Rebellion againſt his <hi>Catholick</hi> Majeſty (their Soveraign Prince) in <hi>Sicily,</hi> and had gotten <hi>Meſſina</hi> into their power, where they had a potent Fleet of Men of War, thereby to give Law to all which ſhould paſs upon the <hi>Mediterranean.</hi> But after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards (becauſe they could not keep it) did moſt perfidiouſly deſert them; whereby thoſe poor people were expoſed to the diſpleaſure of an inraged Prince, and to the greateſt miſeries and calamities imaginable. A fair warning to all ambitious and diſcontented perſons, who ſhall quit their Allegiance which they owe to their natural Prince.</p>
            <p>They are continually brooding of Miſchief, and labouring to enlarge their Empire, herein imitating the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi> who firſt ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Aſia Minor,</hi> then he paſſed over into <hi>Europe,</hi> and conquered all <hi>Greece;</hi> next he falls upon <hi>Syria, Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Armenia,</hi> till at laſt he came as far as <hi>Moldavia</hi> and <hi>Hungary.</hi> And doth not the <hi>French Cabal</hi> obſerve the ſame method? conquering or ſurprizing one Dominion after another; by Arms endeavouring to reduce the Seventeen Provinces under his Obedience, and alſo <hi>Germany;</hi> labouring ſome of the Princes thereof to ſtand Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral, working others to their Party by propoſals of Matches and other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices; and will in ſhort time (if not prevented) ſhake hands with the other Grand Seignior of <hi>Aſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They have now in deſigne, by the power of their Arms, to procure the <hi>Dauphin</hi> to be elected <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Romans.</hi> Are not the perſons and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the three Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Electors,</hi> and of the <hi>Prince Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> every hour expoſed to the Violences and Irruptions of the Arms of the <hi>French?</hi> It may eaſily be foreſeen (without the help of <hi>Galileas</hi> Proſpective) whether by force or promiſes (which will never be kept) they may not give their Suffrages for that ambitious Crown; and how far the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> may be prevailed with, by reaſon of that diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Peace patched up at the Congreſs at <hi>Nimmeguen,</hi> a little time will diſcover. But if the <hi>Dauphin</hi> ſhall be advanced to the Imperial Dignity, will not <hi>Germany</hi> become a Province to the <hi>French</hi> Monarchy? (the fatal conſequences whereof let <hi>Europe</hi> ſoberly conſider.) Can the Princes thereof expect better terms than they have given to the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Lorrain?</hi> For certain, the Proteſtants will be ſure of the ſame uſage and infelicities which the poor <hi>Hugonots</hi> are now under in <hi>France:</hi> For Fire and Fagot muſt be prooemial to his Univerſal Monarchy.</p>
            <p>Diſſimulation is the beſt ſupport of the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt, and the firſt ſtep to their Grandeur: And to deal plainly with you, that <hi>Prince</hi> which will lay the foundation of Empire by <hi>Cruelty,</hi> muſt build the Superſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures by <hi>diſſimulation.</hi> The whole Globe of Miſeries, Calamities, and Infelicities, which <hi>Europe</hi> hath ſuffered for many years, we muſt own to the unlucky contrivance and ambitious deſignes of the <hi>French Cabal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If there be not a Retrenchment of the Grandeur and Potency of that aſpiring <hi>Monarch,</hi> I have ſo much of an <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> in me, that I can fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel what will be the fate of <hi>Europe: France,</hi> like a perpetual <hi>Aetna,</hi> will fling Fire and Flames, Bloud and Confuſion, into the Dominions of the Kings and Princes of <hi>Europe;</hi> and will be more dreadful to his Neighbours, than the Indian Hurricanes are to the Natives there.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101686:7"/>The common Inſcription of his Cannon, <hi>Ratio ultima Regum,</hi> is by him inverted to a contrary ſence, and made a publick Warning to mankind, That he deſignes, as God did of old, to give Law to the world in Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Lightning: To ſcatter by the flames of his Artillery, all thoſe Clouds of Confederate Forces that ſhall eclipſe the Majeſty of his Glory. He makes the power of his Arms, his firſt and laſt reaſon.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Device,</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> in its Meridian, with this Motto, <hi>Non pluribus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par,</hi> ſufficiently ſhews his intentions for the Univerſal Monarchy; and the haughty opinion he conceives of his being the onely perſon qualified for the government of more Worlds than one, declares his reſolutions of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting no Rivals in Soveraignty; looking upon all other Princes but as ſo many ſmaller <hi>Stars</hi> or wandring <hi>Planets,</hi> compared with him the <hi>Sun,</hi> from whom they are to receive their borrowed light or power as it ſhall pleaſe his <hi>Mightineſs</hi> to diſpence. So that crowned heads, Princes, and Republicks, as well as their Subjects, are to expect the ſame meat of Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; and though that be not ſweat, yet the Sawce will be four, <hi>Poinant</hi> to all, though perhaps a little differenced. The former may be allowed <hi>Golden,</hi> while the latter are to be manacled with <hi>Iron</hi> Chains.</p>
            <p>And be aſſured, he that makes War for his Glory, hath more ambition to put his Chains on Princes and States, than on their People. His thoughts are as large as any of the <hi>Roman Emperours;</hi> and they eſteemed it a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory to lead one <hi>King</hi> in Triumph, than a thouſand <hi>Subjects</hi> of ſeveral Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>He doth purpoſe to make all <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Europe</hi> Vaſſals and Tributaries to his Univerſal <hi>Empire;</hi> and rather than fail, he hath deſigned to bring in the <hi>Turks,</hi> (with whom, they will tell you, they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted an entire Friendſhip) in whoſe Court he hath found help to make his Coin currant. Nor is that <hi>infallible</hi> man at <hi>Rome</hi> to eſcape, at leaſt to the Temporal part of his power, which he hath not as he ought employed for the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt; but will abrogate that great Authority in which his Predeceſſors <hi>Pipin</hi> and <hi>Charlemain</hi>'s Charity have veſted him; and without doubt, will pull down his <hi>Spiritual Grandeur,</hi> by fixing it in a <hi>Gallican Patriarch:</hi> and ſo his <hi>Holineſs,</hi> inſtead of being <hi>Chriſts Vicar,</hi> will be made a <hi>French Curate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſome of the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> which now ſeem un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned, will, when it's too late, repent the overſight.</p>
            <p>Sir, it's ſtoried, when <hi>Beaſts</hi> had <hi>Kings,</hi> the <hi>Lions</hi> had the Soveraignty every one of them within his peculiar Foreſt. Whiles their ſtrengths were equal, they lived neighbourly; none inſulted over the other: At laſt time produced a <hi>Lion</hi> ſtronger than the reſt, who diſdaining to be kept within the Precincts left by his Progenitors, preyed upon the Foreſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning: The other Lions fearing their particular Eſtates or Walks, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted for remedy; the way reſolved upon, was to pare his Nails.</p>
            <p>Your Prudence, Sir, will eaſily make the Moral.</p>
            <p>Certainly, it's the true Intereſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> for all <hi>Kings, Princes,</hi> and <hi>States</hi> to unite for their common ſafety, and to act in concert; and not onely to chaſe that ambitious and aſpiring Prince out of his new Conqueſts, but to confine him to his ancient Empire, and his own Dominions.</p>
            <p>A devouring Lion which is never ſatiated with Prey, muſt be chained up.</p>
            <p>The Conqueſt of <hi>Naples</hi> by <hi>Charles</hi> the Eighth, occaſioned a Conſede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy of all the Neighbouring Princes againſt him; whereby he ſoon loſt that he had gotten.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101686:8"/>Look into <hi>Aſia,</hi> did not the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> pick up one Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth after another (the one giving no Aid or Aſſiſtance to the other, but looking on with their hands in their pockets) till at laſt he reduced them all under his Empire? and what was the fatal conſequence thereof, is well known.</p>
            <p>How much more then are the Arms of <hi>France</hi> to be dreaded, whoſe power is mightier than that was of the <hi>Turks!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And every new acqueſt and acceſſion of Territories enlarges his deſires, and makes that Prince think, that which before ſeemed not onely difficult but impoſſible, to be eaſie and feaſable.</p>
            <p>Ambition is never ſo high, but it ſtill thinks to mount; and that Station which lately ſeemed the top, is but a ſtep to her now; and what before was great in deſiring, ſeems little, being once in power.</p>
            <p>The Succeſſes of the <hi>French</hi> have already made them think no Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize too hard, and ſtill prompts them to puſh on their good fortune; which nothing can withſtand, but a general oppoſition of all the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Europe. Dum ſinguli pugnant, univerſi vincuntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I muſt confeſs you are obliged in all duty to acknowledge his <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> of <hi>Great Britain</hi>'s incomparable Wiſdom, great Vigilancy, and dextrous Conduct of Affairs, that you have been hitherto preſerved in Peace and Proſperity, when the whole Neighbourhood hath been infeſted with Fire and Sword, and had no other Proſpect but Bloud and Confuſion.</p>
            <p>But by ſad experience you will finde, that if you do not vigorouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute your Aſſiſtance to put a ſtop to the progreſs of the French Arms, that the natural ſtrength and ſcituation of <hi>England,</hi> can be no ſufficient defence againſt the power of <hi>France,</hi> when to that he hath already, is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all the reſt of <hi>Europe;</hi> unleſs you can dream that your Fleets by Sea and Armies at Land are able to contraſt and ſecure you againſt that power which hath ſubdued all <hi>Europe.</hi> I have obſerved, that the neglect of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, many times makes the Diſeaſe mortal and incurable. The viva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and boldneſs of briſk Reſolutions, always bring forth fortunate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and glorious concluſions. The way down hill is eaſie and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary; but to aſcend unto the top of Glory, requireth Wiſdom to frame the ſteps, and Courage to give the attempt.</p>
            <p>As ſudden Reſolutions are always dangerous, ſo no leſs peril enſueth of ſlow and doubtful Delays. In times of Danger, it's more ſafe to be found in Action than Counſel.</p>
            <q>Cunctatio ſervilis, ſtatim exequi regium est.</q>
            <p>I am in my Conſtellation under <hi>Mercury,</hi> not <hi>Mars,</hi> and deſire Peace; but I am of that Princes minde, not to take up Peace at the intereſt of Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to enſue. A wiſe State ought to deſire Peace; but it's neceſſary to be prepared for War.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Puglia</hi> in <hi>Naples,</hi> if any be bitten by a <hi>Tarantula,</hi> it's not to be cured but by Muſick onely. You are bitten in your Trade, and wounded in your Traffick; there is nothing will cure you but the noiſe of Cannon, and ſound of Drum and Trumpet.</p>
            <p>But you are pleaſed to ſay that you are in League with <hi>France,</hi> and a Rupture on your part would be unjuſt; it's not honourable to break Leagues, which are the Tye and Cement of Nations.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King will grant us any terms.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101686:8"/>I do not deny, but he will grant you any terms; but the more advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious terms you have (if you conſider the <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Nation) the more ought it to be your fear and jealouſie of their breaking of them. But when <hi>France</hi> ſhall be brought to more Equality, better and more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous Conditions will be drawn from him, and he will be well adviſed before he break them.</p>
            <p>Sir, I muſt tell you, there is no Faith or Truſt in <hi>France,</hi> but in its puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance to do hurt. <hi>France</hi> hath ever preferr'd intereſt of State before the faith of Treaties and Leagues; and that made the Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> obſerve, that Princes command over the People, and Intereſt commands over Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>Leagues and Alliances, as they are made for Intereſt, ſo Intereſt will diſſolve them; and foreign Friendſhip laſts no longer than it's advanced with mutual Intereſt.</p>
            <p>All Leagues and Alliances made with <hi>France,</hi> are but as the <hi>Rod</hi> of <hi>Mercury,</hi> to charm them aſleep with whom they are made.</p>
            <p>It was truely obſerved by <hi>Lyſander</hi> the <hi>Greek,</hi> that Children are to be deceived with Toys, but Princes with Oaths and Leagues: And you know it's a prime <hi>Maxime</hi> in the <hi>Cabal</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> That Leagues and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances are to be made for Intereſt, and not on deſigne to keep them: For a Prince ought not to be a Slave to his Faith or Word.</p>
            <p>What Leagues, Alliances, or Treaties can be reckoned, which the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters have not violated? Have they not broken the famous <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty confirmed by Oaths and Sacraments, and contrary to a ſolemn Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation, and the double Tyes of Bloud and Marriage? Before a Breach complained of, or a War declared, they invaded the Territories of an Infant King. Have they not by Addreſſes and Cunning, by Bribes and Rewards, endeavoured to corrupt moſt of the Miniſters of State in <hi>Europe?</hi> How well they have kept the Articles of Peace concluded at <hi>Weſtphalia</hi> and <hi>Nimmeguen,</hi> the <hi>Emperour, King</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> can tell you. And can you prudently hope that the future Practices of the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King will be more juſt than his former? He that hath broken thorow ſo many Obligations, Alliances, and Treaties, will he not do ſo again?</p>
            <p>Be aſſured, Sir, you cannot anchor any faith or confidence in the Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance or Friendſhip of <hi>France;</hi> for <hi>France</hi> is a <hi>floating Iſland,</hi> and no <hi>Terra firma.</hi> It's prudence to keep an Enemy at the Swords <hi>point,</hi> and not to ſuffer him to come within you. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Dominions are the Fountain from whence you draw a great part of your Traffick, and by conſequence your Riches.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Netherlands</hi> are the <hi>Out works</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> if they are taken, you are weak and diſmantled. And let me tell you, Sir, the <hi>day</hi> of the Ruine of <hi>Flanders,</hi> is the <hi>eve</hi> of the Subverſion of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> ſhould be brought under the ſubjection of <hi>France,</hi> it would be a thing of that dreadful conſequence, that the very thoughts of it muſt needs raiſe the bloud of all true Engliſh men. They are ſo ſcituated, that ſeveral of the greateſt Rivers in <hi>Europe</hi> not onely run thorow their Country, but diſembogue into the Ocean within their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts. "If the <hi>French</hi> make themſelves Maſters of the <hi>Rivers,</hi> (as it's their deſigne and endeavour) will they not in a ſhort time bring all the <hi>Havens,</hi> and all the Inhabitants bordering upon the Sea, under the ſame ſubjection?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101686:9"/>The Sea-ports without the Rivers, and the Rivers without the Sea-ports, being altogether uſeleſs; if they be reduced under the Obedience of the <hi>French,</hi> their Country will be the Nurſery of his Sea-men, and in all other reſpects the ſupport of his Naval ſtrength. If they muſt be Slaves, will it not be ſome ſatisfaction to them to lend a helping hand to bring their Neighbours, and in truth all <hi>Europe,</hi> into the ſame condition with themſelves?</p>
            <p>The conquering of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> is not onely a fair ſtep, but it's the beſt part of the way to the Univerſal Monarchy: They being conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> will of courſe fall into their hands, being the <hi>Key</hi> which opens the door to the Throne of that Monarchy. And if you do not act vigorouſly with the reſt of the Confederates, the Moſt <hi>Catholick</hi> King will be enforced to take new Meaſures, and break with you.</p>
            <p>I need not uſe many words to make all <hi>England</hi> ſenſible of the ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> War: 1. The ſeizure of all your Merchants Eſtates, amounting in the whole to a vaſt ſum. 2. The loſs of your Trade with them; which of all others is the moſt beneficial to <hi>England,</hi> and without which your Woollen draperies muſt lie upon your hands, and half of your Weavers and Spinners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> go a begging. 3. The interruption of your <hi>Levant</hi> and Plantation-trade, which cannot in caſe of a Breach, be ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by ordinary Convoys With what encouragement or ſafety can your Traders venture abroad, when the Seas come to be infeſted with <hi>Oſtenders, Biſcainers, Majorcans,</hi> and <hi>Minorcans?</hi> Did not thoſe very men, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any help, take above 1500 Ships from you in the late <hi>Spaniſh</hi> War, when <hi>Spain</hi> was at the loweſt, and fought alone againſt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France?</hi> I could offer many other reaſons, but I am unwilling to be troubleſome.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>French</hi> King ſuffered the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Alenſon</hi> his Brother to take upon him the Title of <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Brabant,</hi> and defence of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, he ſent an Embaſſadour into <hi>Spain</hi> to excuſe his Brother's going thither, and ſignifie unto the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King, that which was done, was done without his privity or conſent. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King was highly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with the Meſſage, and anſwered the Embaſſadour, That he had rather have the <hi>French</hi> King his <hi>profeſſed</hi> Enemy, than a <hi>diſſembling</hi> Friend. And whether <hi>England</hi> ought not to have the ſame Sentiments, I pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> have no kindneſs for <hi>England,</hi> but an inlaid and heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Malice againſt them. When <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France</hi> ſent an Army into <hi>England</hi> to the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Barons</hi> there, againſt King <hi>John</hi> their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Prince, he vowed utterly to <hi>extinguiſh</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; whom he held vile, unjuſt, perfidious, and never to be truſted, as it was declared with much compunction by Viſcount <hi>Melun,</hi> a French Gentleman, lying at the point of death.</p>
            <p>And I can eaſily believe that the ſame Rancor doth yet run in the veins of the <hi>French.</hi> I pray, Sir, who contrived and encouraged the Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the <hi>Scots</hi> againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt? was it not <hi>France?</hi> And the Peace at <hi>Rippon, Anno</hi> 1639. being concluded between the two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (but much againſt their will,) did not <hi>France</hi> ſtir them up to break that Peace, and to make a ſecond attempt by their Arms on <hi>England?</hi> Which they durſt never have done, if they had not received countenance and encouragement from <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By their Emiſſaries they formed a Rebellion in <hi>England,</hi> and underhand
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101686:9"/>ſupported it; and his Majeſties Forces being defeated and broken, <hi>France</hi> look'd on till that great King was ſacrificed to the Tyranny of his worſt Enemies. His now moſt Sacred Majeſty (<hi>England</hi> being hang'd all with Blacks, and the beſt of his Subjects weeping over the Kingdoms funeral) for the ſafety of his perſon, retired into <hi>France;</hi> where he might have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected protection from ſo near a Relation, and comfort as a diſtreſſed <hi>Prince,</hi> but found none: for by virtue of an execrable Treaty made with the then Uſurper, he was forced to forſake that Kingdom, or elſe would have been reſigned up to <hi>Cromwel.</hi> For the chief Article of that Alliance was, That his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> the <hi>Dukes</hi> of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> with all their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Friends, ſhould be expelled out of, and no more admitted into the Kingdom of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>French</hi> King had had the leaſt trillo or touch of Honour in him, he would never have yielded to ſuch a Condition, as to baniſh out of his Kingdom thoſe who came to him for ſuccour and relief, in the utmoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity that ever Princes were put to; and they his neareſt Relations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Siſters Children. And what could be more unbecoming ſo great a <hi>Prince,</hi> than to make a League Offenſive with him who had murdered their Father, and expelled them out of their Dominions?</p>
            <p>What was this but the owning of that Murder, and aggravating their Oppreſſions inſtead of relieving of them? Such practices as theſe amongſt private Chriſtians would be abominable, and much more amongſt any <hi>Kings,</hi> not ſtiled the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you may obſerve, that neither Honour or Relations, can ſtand in competition with Self-intereſt.</p>
            <p>Did they not oppoſe his <hi>Majeſties</hi> reſtauration to the <hi>Emperial Crown</hi> of his <hi>Royal</hi> Anceſtors? Did they not cabal with his greateſt Enemies, to keep him out of his Kingdom? Of which his now Majeſty was ſo ſenſible, that upon his coming into <hi>England,</hi> he commanded away the French Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour <hi>Bordeux,</hi> and would not ſuffer him to come into his preſence.</p>
            <p>In the times of the Uſurpation in <hi>England,</hi> they were the miſchievous Inſtruments of the War between you and the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> as they were of the two following in 1665. and 1671. dreading no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than a durable and firm Friendſhip between the two Nations; blowing up the Fends on both ſides, pretending to take part with each, that they might with leſs oppoſition invade their Neighbours, and increaſe their Naval ſtrength; but not really purpoſing it with either, having the ſame deſigne of weakening both Parties (for your weakneſs is his ſtrength) as the <hi>Britans</hi> formerly had in throwing the Apple of Contention between the <hi>Picts</hi> and the <hi>Scots,</hi> that they might in the end be the better able to overcome both.</p>
            <p>When you had Victory in your palms, and Triumphs in your proſpect, it was raviſhed from you by their means.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Munſter,</hi> who was his now Majeſties Allie, and in Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaid <hi>States,</hi> was neceſſitated to withdraw his Forces (for the ſecurity of his own Territories) becauſe they ſent their Troops againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> wrought <hi>Denmark</hi> off from your Party, and hindered the <hi>Swedes</hi> to arm in favour of you, and contrived that Affront you ſuffered (to your ſhame and diſhonour) at <hi>Chatham.</hi> They have made it their Maſter-piece to raiſe Jealouſies between you and the <hi>Dutch;</hi> and at laſt ſided with the <hi>Dutch</hi> in a War againſt you, not with any intention for themſelves to fight, but to ſee you deſtroy each other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101686:10"/>Did they not moſt treacherouſly put to the ſword and ſlavery, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Subjects in St. <hi>Chriſtophers,</hi> plundered them of all which by their induſtry and providence they had for many years acquired?</p>
            <p>But a Peace at <hi>Breda</hi> being concluded, the <hi>French</hi> were by the Treaty to return to his Majeſty St. <hi>Chriſtophers</hi> in ſuch ſort as therein is expreſſed. But inſtead of performing it according to the true meaning, and the very letter of the Article, they upon ſeveral unjuſt and frivolous pretences, did not deliver it in four years to the Commiſſioners which were ſent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it: For it's againſt the Candor and Integrity of the <hi>French Cabal,</hi> to part with any thing that may be of conveniency for them to keep. But at laſt they delivered it to Sir <hi>Charles Wheeler;</hi> but before the delivery of it, they deſtroyed all the Plantations, plundred and carried away all that was there, laid the whole Country waſte, and left it in a much worſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that if it had never been planted.</p>
            <p>And as if the detaining of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Territories had not been ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, they interrupted the Trade of his Subjects in thoſe parts, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming to themſelves the Soveraignty of thoſe Seas, they would not ſuffer any Ships but their own to ſail by or about their <hi>Iſlands;</hi> and upon no other ground, have brought in as Prizes, and confiſcated many Veſſels.</p>
            <p>In 1674, &amp; 1675. when the <hi>Dutch</hi> and Neighbour-Nations were in War, but <hi>England</hi> in Peace, who thereby expecting a great Trade, bought many Dutch-built Veſſels; the King of <hi>England</hi> accordingly granted them his Licenſe to trade in them, by reaſon of the Act of Navigation.</p>
            <p>But <hi>France,</hi> to hinder the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> iſſued out an <hi>Edict</hi> for the ſeizing of all Ships bought in any Enemies Country. And in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their <hi>Edicts,</hi> there came out a ſwarm of <hi>French Capers,</hi> who not onely ſeized on thoſe <hi>Dutch-built Ships,</hi> though they had his Majeſties Licenſe, but ſinding the ſweetneſs of that Trade, ſeized upon your <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built Ships,</hi> on pretence they carried Enemies goods, whilſt they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves would be Judges; they did actually ſeize all <hi>Engliſh-built</hi> Veſſels meerly laden on the account of being <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, and retook ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which had been diſcharged in <hi>France;</hi> they plundered your Ships, and wounded your Sea-men.</p>
            <p>There were about 400 fail of your Merchants Ships ſeized by them in this manner, many of which the <hi>French</hi> did abſolutely condemn; and ſuch as were releaſed, were kept ſome <hi>three</hi> months, ſome <hi>ſix</hi> months, ſome <hi>twelve</hi> months, and others longer; and then were diſcharged with great damage by expence and plunder in <hi>France,</hi> beſides the firſt affronts and violences. And after all, you loſt the intended Fruit of your Voyages; and what was yet worſe, they making the moſt advantages of every thing, got many thouſands of your Sea-men by extraordinary Pay to engage in his ſervice. And that which may ſuper-adde Calamity to your Miſery, when the <hi>French</hi> did forbear to take your Ships, the <hi>Algerines</hi> (Allies of <hi>France,</hi> and by them ſet up) have continually pickt up your Merchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Vaſſalized your Sea men ever ſince. And what they take from you, they carry into the <hi>French</hi> Harbours, where the <hi>French</hi> buy the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities at their own prices.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you the great diſcouragements your <hi>French Trade</hi> hath for many years lain under, through their unjuſt practices, and manifold devices.</p>
            <p>Nor ſhall I ſpeak now how by their <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> and <hi>Factories</hi> of Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they have contrived and brooded a moſt execrable Plot in <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101686:10"/>and other his Majeſties Kingdoms; and have ſown Diviſions, Diſcontents, and Jealouſies amongſt his good Subjects; thereby to prevent his Majeſties Royal inclinations in giving his aſſiſtance to his oppreſſed Neighbours, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that great Prince.</p>
            <p>If theſe Enormities and Super-injuſtices of the <hi>French Cabal,</hi> be not ſufficient to awaken <hi>England,</hi> conſiderate men will wonder what <hi>Opiate</hi> hath caſt you aſleep; and if you be not enchanted by the Magick of <hi>French Piſtols.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray, Sir, draw the Curtain; open your eyes, and ſee if the Liberty of all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> be not now at ſtake! Do you think it will adde any Trophies to your Glory, when Poſterity ſhall ſay, It was <hi>England</hi> which advanced the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King into the Throne of an Univerſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy?</p>
            <p>Is it not your intereſt to oppoſe that <hi>Power</hi> which oppoſeth all <hi>Europe,</hi> and labours to bury it in the Grave of Infamy and Slavery?</p>
            <p>If you be backward to give your Aſſiſtance, when you may have ſo many Allies, what will you do when their Forces are broken, and you are enforced ſingly to <hi>contrast</hi> the Power of <hi>France</hi> and its new Acqueſts? What you may expect from his <hi>Mightineſs,</hi> enquire of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> and of the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> and they will tell you. The Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Britiſh Sea (which is your Glory, and ought to be your Care) is gone.</p>
            <p>He will give Law to your Commerce; and <hi>Navigation</hi> which is now your <hi>Honour,</hi> will be nothing but a <hi>Piracy</hi> to you; and <hi>England,</hi> for want of Trade, (being an Iſland) will be nothing but a Priſon to you.</p>
            <p>You which are the great Merchants, and ſo famous in the world for your Traffick, muſt become <hi>Higlers</hi> and petty Chapmen under him. Your Men of War (which are now a Terrour to your Neighbours) will be of no uſe to you, but to make your Slavery the greater: Your gallant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders and Sea-men (as the <hi>Romans</hi> ſerved the <hi>Britans</hi> when they had conquered them) will be ſent into foreign Dominions to advance their Empire. And if he ſhall ſuffer any of you by his favour to grow rich and full, it's onely like Spunges to be ſqueezed. You muſt like the Camel down upon your knees, and receive what burthens he ſhall pleaſe to lay upon your backs. You are now a flouriſhing and well-<hi>Creſted</hi> People, you have your Liberty and Freedoms (which you ought to value above a Crown;) but if you come within the power of <hi>France,</hi> you will be ſuch Slaves, as you will not be capable of a <hi>Jubile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King ſhould be ſo kind and merciful unto you, as to obſerve his Alliance with you tell he hath reduced all other <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> under his Obedience, yet you cannot but expect <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemus</hi> Curteſie, to be the laſt which ſhall be eaten up. Whereas if we all aſſociate and unite, and act potently againſt that aſpiring Prince, we are freed of all fears and jealouſies; and it's not poſſible for him to be other than the <hi>French</hi> King. And then inſtead of an Univerſal <hi>Monarchy</hi> (which is the deſigue of <hi>France</hi>) there will be <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> an Univerſal Peace; of which his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> will have the honour: for by the power of his Arms it's onely to be effected.</p>
            <p>A timely War is leſs dangerous, than an uncertain Peace; and ſuch is your condition with <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A War will fall upon you; and it's a great overſight to have been ſo modeſt as to abide the taking of the firſt blow. Wiſdom teacheth us,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101686:11"/>that in Warlike actions the having of the ſtart, and to ſtrike firſt, is a great advantage; it puts the Enemy to the defenſive, which is no other than fighting for his own ſtake.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans,</hi> as long as they were <hi>Defendants,</hi> were miſerable; and <hi>Antiochus</hi> refuſing <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s counſel to invade <hi>Italy,</hi> was put to the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive,</hi> wherein he loſt his Life and Crown.</p>
            <p>The charge of the invading <hi>Prince</hi> is certainly known; if he like not the Attempt, he may deſiſt at pleaſure. Whereas the invaded is not onely at the charge to maintain Armies, but his Territories are inſtantly impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhed, his Revenues deminiſhed, Trade and Commerce laid aſide, his good Subjects with fear amazed, the Ill-affected who deſirous of change, apt to run to the Enemy; and many other Miſchiefs will fall upon you, whereof you cannot be eaſed, but at the pleaſure of the Invader. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Money to be diſburſed for the War <hi>offenſive,</hi> eſpecial with you in <hi>Great Britain,</hi> where Victuals, Arms, Shipping, and other Habiliments for the War abound, runs into the Subjects purſe, and the Realm is little or nothing impoveriſhed by it. But to forbid and attend the deſcents of the Invader (if we be on the defenſive part) your Fleet muſt neceſſarily be divided; the conſequence whereof (conſidering the Potency of their Naval power) I am afraid will prove, that you will be too weak in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Squadrons of your ſhattered Navy.</p>
            <p>I ſhould be ſorry to ſee <hi>Great Britain</hi> become a <hi>Province</hi> to the <hi>French Monarchy,</hi> and be made a <hi>Theatre</hi> where the <hi>Tragedy</hi> of <hi>Monieurs</hi> perſeen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be acted; and the good <hi>Proteſtants</hi> there ſuffer the ſame Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, Baniſhment, and Miſeries for the Liberty of their Conſcience, as the poor <hi>Hugonots</hi> have done in <hi>France</hi> for the exerciſe of their Religion. I do aſſure you, Sir, you cannot expect better terms than the <hi>Hugonots</hi> now have in <hi>France.</hi> With what Infelicities, preſſures in Gonſcience, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietude of Mind, and how precariouſly they do poſſeſs, but not enjoy their Eſtates, gotten with Sweat, and kept by Care, I need not tell you.</p>
            <p>It was not the method of <hi>Christ</hi> to force Belief by Slaughters, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct mens Conſciences by the Sword; yet theſe are the Arguments which they apply to convince thoſe unhappy Souls.</p>
            <p>Sir, there is no ſafety in depending upon the Charity of <hi>France;</hi> I muſt tell you again, the onely ſecurity of all <hi>Chriſtian Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> is their impuiſſance to do hurt. The end of War is Peace; but a Peace with <hi>France</hi> ſeems to me to be the beginning of War: And though War be a great Evil, yet from all appearances, I dread the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of a Peace more. If the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King ſhall diſband his Forces, it's far from being any ſecurity, ſince he may raiſe them again at his pleaſure; nor is it to be imagined that he will ſo do, ſince that were to give his People an opportunity of rebelling, for which he is ſenſible they are ſufficiently prepared, and onely want <hi>Domeſtick</hi> Heads and Partiſans, or foreign Aſſiſtance, to reſcue them from Tyranny and Oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>And whiles ſo potent a <hi>Monarch</hi> is in Arms, all <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> will be obliged for their own ſafety, to keep up ſtanding Armies; which Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges will aſſuredly undo them: for it's a declared <hi>Maxime</hi> in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, That there is no better way to ruine the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> than to oblige them to keep Armies on Foot. For thoſe require great expences, which will impoveriſh them, and by conſequence precipitate their Ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101686:11"/>Juſt Fears, are a juſt cauſe of War; and a preventive War, is a true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, as well as a War upon an actual Invaſion, though offenſively acted.</p>
            <p>Hence the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> (as <hi>Thucydides</hi> tell us) armed againſt the <hi>Athenians,</hi> by reaſon of their over-growing Greatneſs. And <hi>Antiochus,</hi> upon this principle, invited <hi>Pruſſias</hi> King of <hi>Bithinia</hi> (at that time in League with the <hi>Romans</hi>) to joyn with him in War againſt them; ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting before him a juſt fear of the over-ſpreading Greatneſs of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and that their deſigne was to reduce all <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> under their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and to make the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> an Univerſal <hi>Monarchy;</hi> that <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Nabis</hi> were already ruinated, and it was his turn to be aſſaulted next. So that thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> or <hi>States</hi> which do deſire too great Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, and ſeek to enlarge their Dominions, do give a juſt fear to their Neighbours.</p>
            <p>That War is juſt which is neceſſary, and then Arms are deemed pious, when they are the laſt Refuge of thoſe which uſe them.</p>
            <p>In elder time, it paſſed for an Oracle of Wiſdom, <hi>Decreſeat Hiſpania, &amp; non Creſcat Gallia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we do make a War againſt that great Diſturber of the Peace of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> as it's our Safety, ſo it is Prudence to make it <hi>ſpeedily</hi> and <hi>powerfully:</hi> for if we do not make it <hi>powerfully,</hi> we ſhall be like the poor woman who bought Coals ſufficient to roaſt her Pig, but laying them on one by one, her Coals were waſted, and her Pig unroaſted: And if we do not make it <hi>ſpeedily,</hi> we ſhall imitate that Emperick who gave Phyſick to a dead man.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Latines</hi> prayed in aid of the <hi>Lavinians</hi> againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> but they put off their reſolution ſo long, that when they were going forth of Town to give Summons to them, News came that the <hi>Latines</hi> were defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; whereupon <hi>Milonius</hi> the <hi>Pretor</hi> ſaid, We ſhall pay deerly to the <hi>Romans</hi> for this little way we are gone. For if they had reſolved not to have given Aid, they had not given offence to the <hi>Romans</hi> by helping of them; and had their Aid come in time with the addition of their own Forces, they might have gained the Victory. But by delays, loſs and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes came every way. And whether this may not be the Caſe of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> I ſubmit it to your great judgment.</p>
            <p>This is not ſuch a War as was between the <hi>Etolians</hi> and <hi>Archadians,</hi> for a <hi>wild Boar,</hi> nor for a <hi>Cart-load</hi> of <hi>Sheep-skins,</hi> as was between <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgondy</hi> and the <hi>Switzers;</hi> nor like that between the <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and <hi>picts,</hi> for a few Dogs: but it's <hi>pro aris &amp; focis.</hi> We fight to preſerve our own Intereſt, and to avoid Beggery and Slavery; which will unavoidably fall upon us, if the Ambition of that aſpiring <hi>Prince</hi> be not ſtinted. When <hi>England</hi> ſhall vigorouſly appear againſt them, the <hi>French King</hi> will be neceſſitated to deſire Peace, and to do Juſtice. The apprehenſion of your Forces will be a terrour unto him, our Allies will be greatly encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, and they with united Forces will act more powerfully. Our Fleets will give them ſuch juſt fears, that they will be obliged to employ ſome great part of their Troops to defend their own Coaſts; and will be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to quit ſome of their new Conqueſts (as they have done <hi>Meſſina</hi>) to ſecure their own Dominions.</p>
            <p>The conquering of Villages and Towns, are like Bonfires of Straw; but if they meet with a ſtout oppoſition, they are mortal as other men, and one good blow will cauſe a <hi>reverter</hi> of all their new Acqueſts.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101686:12"/>It's ſtoried, that <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>fifth,</hi> after he had claſped <hi>Germany</hi> almoſt in his fiſt, he was forced in the end to go from <hi>Juſprug</hi> as if it had been in a Maſque by Torch-light, and to give up every foot in <hi>Germany</hi> that he had gotten. Which I doubt not will be the Hereditary fate of the late Purchaſes and Conqueſts of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know the Moſt <hi>Chriſtian King</hi> hath as many experienced Captains and diſciplined Souldiers, as any <hi>Prince</hi> in <hi>Europe;</hi> but that ſorts to the honour of the Engliſh, ſeeing they ever have had the better of it in all Rencoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and never left the Field but with Glory.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> Valour lieth to the eye of the lookers on, but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Courage lieth about the Souldiers heart; and the Fury of the <hi>French,</hi> the firſt blaſt being over, turns to Fear.</p>
            <p>No <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Prince</hi> hath ſuch a ſpring and ſeminary of brave Military people, as be in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and who will be ready to ſacrifice their Lives for their King and Country.</p>
            <p>Where was <hi>Caeſar</hi> in greater danger than in <hi>England?</hi> Where was there a <hi>Prince</hi> that durſt challenge him to a ſingle Combat, but in <hi>England?</hi> The <hi>Romans</hi> conquered <hi>Gallia</hi> in ten years, whereas they did not ſubdue <hi>England</hi> in 200 years; and not then, till they had conquered all the reſt of the World: Becauſe they reſerved the Conqueſt of <hi>England</hi> (as Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors uſe to do moſt commonly in great Enterprizes) for the laſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Conqueſt that they had to do.</p>
            <p>If you will conſult the <hi>Regiſter</hi> of times, you will obſerve <hi>England</hi> never had any Encounter with <hi>France,</hi> but it came off with Honour.</p>
            <p>I ſhall give you a particular Liſt of ſome of them in an Hiſtorical truth, no ways ſtrouted nor made greater by Language; that's becoming a General at the head of an Army, when they are going to Battle, but not with me: And I ſhall begin with that at <hi>Creſſey,</hi> the firſt great Battel.</p>
            <p>That Heroick King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> having been provoked by divers Affronts that <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Valois</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King had offered him, goes over in perſon into <hi>France</hi> with an Army of 8000 men at <hi>Arms,</hi> and 10000 <hi>Archers;</hi> he takes with him his Son the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Guyenne,</hi> being but <hi>fifteen</hi> years of age (called afterwards the <hi>black Prince</hi>) to train him up in feats of Arms. Landing in <hi>Normandy,</hi> he marches within ten miles of <hi>Paris;</hi> and after divers Skirmages, a Battel was appointed. King <hi>Edward</hi> incamped near a Village called <hi>Creſſey;</hi> the <hi>French Kings</hi> Army was above twice the number, conſiſting of above 60000, with all the Flower of the <hi>French</hi> Nobility. The Battle began, the Fight grew hot and doubtful, inſomuch that the Commanders ſent to King <hi>Edward</hi> (who was gotten into a Wind-mill, where, as from a Centinel, he might behold the face of the Enemy) to come up with more power: the King aſked the Meſſenger whether his Son was hurt or ſlain; and being anſwered no, he replies, Then tell them who ſent you, that ſo long as my Son is alive, they ſend no more to me; for my will is, that he have the honour of the day. The Fight on both ſides was very furious; the <hi>French</hi> King having his horſe killed under him, withdrew; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing known to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> it added ſo to their Courage, that they ſoon after won the Field. This Battle was ſo bloudy, that there were none made Priſoners, but all put to the Sword. The number of the ſlain <hi>French,</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted the whole Army of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> for the number of the ſlain were about <hi>thirty</hi> thouſand.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101686:12"/>The next great Victory in <hi>France,</hi> was the Battle of <hi>Poitiers.</hi> The <hi>black Prince</hi> being tapred up now to a good growth, was ſent by advice of Parliament to <hi>Gaſcony,</hi> the Truce being expired: He ravaged the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try as far as <hi>Tourane. John</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King raiſeth a potent Army more numerous than that at <hi>Creſſey;</hi> and going to finde out the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> found him about <hi>Poitiers,</hi> not much above 10000 men effective in his Army. The <hi>Prince</hi> finding the main ſtrength of the <hi>French</hi> Army con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in Horſe, he intrenched amongſt the Vineyards; where when the <hi>French</hi> Cavalry entred, being wrapt and intangled amongſt the Vines, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Archers did ſo ply and gall them, that thereby being defeated and put to rout, the whole Army was ſoon defected. In this Battel King <hi>John</hi> himſelf was taken priſoner, whom the <hi>Prince</hi> brought into <hi>England,</hi> where he continued <hi>four</hi> years: And as the French <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, he was ſo nobly received, that he knew not whether he was a <hi>free King</hi> or a <hi>Captive.</hi> Beſides Lords and Nobles that were ſlain in this Battle, there were upon the whole more French ſlain, than the whole Engliſh Army was in number.</p>
            <p>We will now to <hi>Agencourt. Henry</hi> the <hi>fifth,</hi> that Mirror of Princes, being come to the Crown, he caſt his eyes towards <hi>France;</hi> and for clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of his Title, he ſent the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Exeter</hi> in a magniſicent Embaſſie to demand the Crown: but receiving no ſatisfactory Anſwer, but rather a kind of Jeer, the <hi>Dauphin</hi> ſending him a Sack full of <hi>Racket-balls</hi> to paſs away his time, he replied, That for every one of thoſe Balls, he had ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Fiery Bullets</hi> to ſhoot at the proudeſt Terrets in <hi>France,</hi> as he ſhould ſhortly find. And he was as good as his word: for he preſently got over, and encountering the <hi>French</hi> Army at <hi>Agencourt,</hi> he gave it an utter Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, and took more priſoners than his own Army had Souldiers. And this <hi>King</hi> made ſo abſolute a Conqueſt of <hi>France,</hi> that <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>ſeventh</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> like a poor <hi>Roy de Juidot,</hi> conſined himſelf to <hi>Burges,</hi> where (having caſhiered his Retinue) he was found in a little Chamber at ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with a Napkin laid before him, a Rump of Mutton, and two Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins.</p>
            <p>There were many other Warlike Encounters betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> whereof the ſtories are full; and it's obſerved, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at moſt were but half, ſometimes not the third or fourth part in number to the <hi>French,</hi> in the Engagements. And though the <hi>Scots</hi> did always con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate with the <hi>French</hi> againſt <hi>England,</hi> and when the King of <hi>England</hi> was in <hi>France,</hi> would for diverſion invade <hi>England,</hi> yet <hi>England</hi> bore up ſingle and victoriouſly againſt them both.</p>
            <p>I muſt beg your pardon, if I cannot omit one ſtory. <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>third</hi> being engaged in <hi>France</hi> with his Army, <hi>David</hi> King of <hi>Scots</hi> with about 60000 men (being a Confederate with the <hi>French</hi> King) invaded <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> Queen <hi>Philippa,</hi> with the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> the Lords and the Knights of the North, encountered the Kings Army and utterly defeated it: The <hi>Scottiſh</hi> King was taken priſoner, and reſerved as a Preſent for <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> when he returned out of <hi>France,</hi> to keep company with <hi>John</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King, taken priſoner by the black Prince. And there were but ſix weeks difference between both Victories.</p>
            <p>Nor were ſuch high Exploits performed by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> on Land onely, but by Sea they have been as glorious. <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King, not long before the Battle of <hi>Creſſey,</hi> to hinder <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>third</hi>'s return into <hi>France,</hi> got a mighty Navy in equipage of 200 ſail of Ships beſides Gallies
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101686:13"/>in the Haven of <hi>Sluce;</hi> where of King <hi>Edward</hi> being advertiſed, prepared ſuch another Fleet, and encounters the <hi>French</hi> with ſuch reſolution and ſucceſs, having the Wind and Sea for him, that he thereby defeated the whole Navy, ſlew about 30000 men, and ſo returned with mighty Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, and the Admiration of all <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the year 1591. was that memorable Fight of an Engliſh Ship called the <hi>Revenge,</hi> under the command of Sir <hi>Richard Greenfield;</hi> memorable, I ſay, beyond credit, and to the hight of ſome Heroical Fable. This Ship for the ſpace of 15 hours, ſate like a Stag amongſt Hounds at the Bay, and was ſeiged and fought with in turn, by 15 great Ships of <hi>Spain,</hi> part of a Navy of 55 Ships in all, the reſt like Abettors looking on a far off. And amongſt the 15 Ships that fought, the great St. <hi>Philip</hi> was one, a Ship of 1500 Tun, Prince of the twelve Sea-Apoſtles, which was glad when ſhe was ſhifted off from the <hi>Revenge.</hi> This brave Ship the <hi>Revenge</hi> was man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely with 200 men, whereof 80 laid ſick; yet nevertheleſs, after a Fight maintained 15 hours, and three Ships of the Enemies ſunk by her ſide, and 15 more of them ſo torn and battered that they periſhed in the Sea before they could recover the <hi>Tercera;</hi> that gallant Ship never came to be entred, but was taken by compoſition, the Enemies themſelves ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in admiration the Vertue of the Commander, and the whole Tragedy of that Ship.</p>
            <p>Nor doth that Primitive innate Courage and Gallantry languiſh or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline in them (as ſome think the World doth, and as we find it doth in other Nations, as the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi>) but it continueth in the ſame height. The ancient Stourneſs and Gallantry of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> appeared in many Traverſes of the late War here in <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> King con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that the Brigade of <hi>Engliſh</hi> before <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> though not the fifth part of the Army, did contribute moſt to the taking of that Preditory Town.</p>
            <p>And I doubt not but when his ſacred Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> ſhall be pleaſed to give his Royal <hi>Fiat,</hi> we ſhall ſee the ſame valiant Bloud is now channelled in the Engliſh veins; and that every Royal Subject will be ready to take <hi>Talbot</hi>'s Motto upon his Sword, <hi>Sum Talboti pro defendendo Rege contra inimicos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that if the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> will take into his Royal Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the Galamities and miſerable condition that all <hi>Europe</hi> is in by the Oppreſſion of the <hi>French,</hi> and their deſignes of an Univerſal Monarchy, and potently act, having ſuch a Warlike People, with the reſt of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates; the Reduction of <hi>France</hi> to its ancient Boundaries, would be no great work.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but that the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England</hi> will give Aid cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (and Sir Money is the <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> that moves the Spheres, which are the hearts and hands of men;) his Majeſties Fame and Power will be admired, his Subjects highly pleaſed, the Nations under his Scepter feared, and it will beget a perfect Union between his Majeſty and all his People; who in a grateful and humble acknowledgement of his Royal Care and Protection of them, will bring to his ſervice a Magazine of Hearts, and to his Coffers a Treaſury of Money, which is the Soveraign Cordial that gives life to all Warlike Actions.</p>
            <p>What the touring and ambitious thoughts of the <hi>French</hi> King ſignifie, his great Preparations by Sea do manifeſt to all <hi>Europe:</hi> for he hath raiſed a greater Naval ſtrength in few years ſince he hath applied himſelf to it,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101686:13"/>than ever yet was raiſed in the world for the time. And if he ſhall year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſe in power at Sea as he hath done for theſe twenty years laſt paſt, the whole world will not be Elbow-room enough for his Ambition.</p>
            <p>Having ſo prodigioully advanced in number of Ships, after he hath gained more Harbours and Ports, as it's his deſigne, and bred up experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Commanders and Sea-men (as no <hi>Prince</hi> can be more induſtrious) he will then pull off the Vizard, and declare that all <hi>Kings, Princes,</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> muſt give Obedience to his <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and become his <hi>Vaſſals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, it's certain, that thoſe States whoſe Renown are greateſt in Story, did eſtabliſh their Supream Dominion upon the Power they attained at Sea. The <hi>Romans</hi> did not impoſe upon the World their Laws, till they had forced the Sea to receive and acknowledge them. Had they not ſet out Warlike Fleets, they had never accompliſhed their glorious deſignes; they had never extended their Fronteers beyond <hi>Italy,</hi> nor brought down the pride of <hi>Garthage,</hi> nor triumphed over all the <hi>Crowns</hi> on Earth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and the <hi>Grecians,</hi> conſidered the Sea as the beſt Support of their Dominions. And whether the deſignes of the <hi>French</hi> King be not as large and great by his <hi>Naval</hi> Preparations, as thoſe of the <hi>Romans, Greeians,</hi> or of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> or <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchs were; it's well ſuiting with the Wiſdom of the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Europe</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</p>
            <p>Be aſſured, Sir, if this Sea-<hi>Gyant</hi> be not timely deſtroyed, but ſuffered like the <hi>Crocadile</hi> yearly to grow in Magnitude, it will devour all <hi>Europe,</hi> and with it it's Trade, Traffick, and Commerce. Therefore it's <hi>Europe</hi>'s Intereſt, as well as <hi>England</hi>'s Safety, to deſtroy the <hi>Naval</hi> Power of <hi>France,</hi> which (with the conjunction of our Allies) may be effected; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once brought down there, their Commerce will wax feeble, and by conſequence their Power at Land will ſoon abate: For we have obſerved, that until the <hi>Spaniards</hi> loſt his <hi>Maratine</hi> Forces, he maintained his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> very vigorouſly, and never ſunk till then.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> King of late is become ſo potent at Sea, that if he ſhould be pleaſed to give trouble to you or to any other Prince, we m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt be at his diſcretion how kindly he will deal with us. And, Sir, it's no wiſdom in any Prince, to depend upon the diſcretion of another.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>State</hi> which is Maſter at Sea, may make a deſcent at what place they pleaſe, unleſs they be hindered by a Fleet of equal ſtrength; and except every Creek, Port, and ſandy Bay, had a powerful Army to make oppoſition. If we have an Army in one place (as in all places we cannot have) then they may by reaſon of their Fleet, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their Army to another place; and ſo take, ranſack, burn, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Country round about: as <hi>Agathocles</hi> did, who being beſieged by the <hi>Carthagenians</hi> in <hi>Syracuſe,</hi> put his Army into his Fleet and tranſported it into <hi>Africa;</hi> and the <hi>Carthagenians,</hi> for ſecurity of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and their own Dominions, were forced to raiſe their Seige and follow with their Army.</p>
            <p>Methinks the Miſeries, Devaſtations, and Infelicities <hi>England</hi> hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuffered by the Naval power of the <hi>Danes,</hi> might teach you wiſdom for the future. Sir, to deal plainly with you, it's impoſſible for any <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitine</hi> Country (as <hi>England</hi> is) though the Coaſts thereof be never ſo well fortified, to defend it ſelf againſt a powerful Enemy that is Maſter at Sea; for a good Fleet of Men of War under a wiſe and judicious conduct,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101686:14"/>need not fear to paſs by the beſt appointed Fort in <hi>Europe</hi> (though never ſo many great Artillery are planted in it) with the help of a good Tyde and leading gale of Wind.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Parma</hi> beſieged <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and finding no poſſibility to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it otherwiſe than by Famine, laid his Cannon on the bank of the River ſo well to purpoſe, and ſo even with the face of the water, that he thought it impoſſible for the leaſt Boat to paſs by; yet the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Zelan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> to ſell their Butter and Cheeſe at <hi>Antwerp</hi> where it was dear, paſſed in their Boats by the mouth of the <hi>Duke</hi>'s Cannon in deſpight of it, when a ſtrong Weſterly wind and a Tyde of flood favoured them, as alſo with a contrary wind and ebbing water they turned back again.</p>
            <p>In the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> when <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweden</hi> were at war, our <hi>Eaſtland</hi> Fleet bound for <hi>Liefland,</hi> was forbidden by the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> to trade with the Subjects of his Enemies; and he threatned to ſink their Ships, if they came through the Streights of <hi>Elſenore:</hi> Yet our Merchants having a Ship of her Majeſties called the <hi>Minion</hi> to defend them, made their adventure, and ſuſtained ſome Vollies of ſhot, but kept on their courſe. The King made all the proviſions he could to ſtop or ſink them at their return; but the <hi>Minion</hi> leading the way, did not onely paſs without loſs, but did beat down with their Artillery a great part of the Fort of <hi>Elſenore;</hi> and the Fleet of Merchants which followed went thorough without any wound received.</p>
            <p>Sir, <hi>Imperator Maris, est Dominus Terrae:</hi> When <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Mark Anthony</hi> at <hi>Actium</hi> fought by Sea for the Empire of the World, <hi>Mark An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi>'s Fleet being defeated, all the People and the Souldiers ſubmitted to <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> well knowing they could never effect any thing by Land, as long as <hi>Auguſtus</hi> continued Maſter at Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aladine</hi> a poor Fiſherman, but famous for his great Actions at Sea, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> King of <hi>Achen</hi> in <hi>Sumatra</hi> preferred him to be his Lord-Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and married him to one of his Kindſwomen, and gave him the care and protection of his Son and Heir; <hi>Aladine</hi> having the Naval power at his command, he murthered the Son and Heir, and uſurped the Kingdom to himſelf, there being no reſiſtance to be made againſt him, becauſe of his great power at Sea.</p>
            <p>The State of <hi>Genoa,</hi> by the advantage of their Naval power, beat the <hi>Piſans</hi> out of <hi>Sardinia, Corſica,</hi> and the <hi>Baleares</hi> in the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> and having vanquiſhed the <hi>Venetian</hi> Fleet, they took the <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Chioggia</hi> not far from <hi>Venice.</hi> But the <hi>Genoeſſes</hi> being diſabled in their Naval power by the overſight of <hi>Peter Doria</hi> their Admiral, they loſt their <hi>Iſlands</hi> in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> to the King of <hi>Aragon; Capha</hi> and <hi>Pera,</hi> and the <hi>Iſlands</hi> of <hi>Lesbos</hi> and <hi>Chio,</hi> with ſome other Iſlands in the <hi>Greek</hi> Sea, to the <hi>Grand Seignior;</hi> and moſt of their Holds in <hi>Tuſcany</hi> (whereof they had a good part) to the <hi>Florentines;</hi> and had nothing left them but <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guria,</hi> and the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Corſica,</hi> and were enforced to put themſelves into the protection of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to preſerve the ſame. Therefore, Sir, you may pleaſe to obſerve how highly <hi>England</hi> (being an Iſland) is concerned in point of intereſt and ſafety, to advance their own Naval power, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate that of others.</p>
            <p>There are <hi>three</hi> great Naval powers in <hi>Europe; England, France,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces;</hi> if the King of <hi>England</hi> joyn with one of them, they will give Law to the third: But what if <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> ſhould joyn againſt <hi>England</hi> (as you have great reaſon to fear
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101686:14"/>they will) if by his Majeſties tranſcendent Wiſdom and happy Conduct, they be not prevented; then you can expect nothing but Confuſion and Ruine to fall upon you. Therefore it will be the very teſt of Prudence in this juncture, to retrench the power of <hi>France</hi> by Sea; that being done, from his Land-forces there can be no great danger to you. At Land the Ballance is indifferently even, but at Sea (which ought to be your care) there is no counterpoize. The fighting and deſtroying of his Land-Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, doth not weaken him at Sea; but when his new Conqueſts ſhall be taken from him, or a Peace concluded, if he ſhould put an Army into his Navy, no Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> is able to hinder his Attempts; and thoſe vaſt ſums of money which he raiſeth out of his Subjects, if they ſhould be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in Traffick, he being ſo potent at Sea, all States and Princes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>England,</hi> would be undone.</p>
            <p>To ſtrike the <hi>French</hi> King at Sea (where his ſtrength lieth) is to cut his <hi>Sampſons</hi> locks; it's <hi>un Coup de Maiſtre;</hi> a Maſter blow; a War in his bowels. To give him ſome light hurt, is dangerous to us, and to give our ſelves an incurable wound; as the Horſe did, who falling out with the Lion, bruiſed him with his heel; but not long after his Carcaſs became food for the Lion. Great Potentates are not at all to be touched; but if they be, they muſt be made ſure from taking Revenge.</p>
            <p>Some conſiderate Princes have begun a War rather with the <hi>Sword</hi> than with a <hi>Trumpet:</hi> So delt the <hi>Aragonoies</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> in <hi>Naples; Henry</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> of <hi>France</hi> with the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> when he went to <hi>Briſac</hi> to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize as many places as he could, before the War broke out; Don <hi>John</hi> with the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> when in the great Imbargo he took all your Ships and Goods in his Ports. And may not the <hi>French</hi> King (if the Capritio ſhall take him) before any denunciation or indiction of War, ſet upon your Fleets of Merchants Ships at Sea? he having ſuch powerful Squadrons of Men of War in all parts, that no Fleet of Merchants with their Convoys, are able to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny oppoſition, but they muſt be ſunk or taken.</p>
            <p>As it was the overſight of the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Europe</hi> (if you pleaſe to pardon the expreſſion) to ſuffer <hi>France</hi> to grow up to that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency and Magnitude of Power at Sea; ſo it will be their wiſdom and intereſt to act in conſort till they have deſtroyed it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:101686:15"/>
               <head>Methods and Arts TO Retrench the Potency OF FRANCE BY LAND and SEA, And to Confine that Ambitious Monarch Within his Antient DOMINIONS and TERRITORIES.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>Humbly ſubmitted to the grave Conſideration of the KINGS and PRINCES of</hi> Europe.</head>
               <p n="1">1. ALL <hi>Kings, Princes,</hi> and <hi>States</hi> to aſſociate, and vigorouſly to act in concert againſt him, and to make <hi>France</hi> the ſeat of the War; if not, by his Contributions and the oppreſſion of his Armies (by which he maintains his own Forces) they will all be ruinated, their Countries waſted, and themſelves muſt be ſubmitted to his power. Whereas by making <hi>France</hi> the ſeat of the War, the Souldiers will be inriched with the Spoils, ſupport themſelves at the coſt and charges of <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King will be neceſſitated to draw his Souldiers out of his new Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, for the defence of his ancient Dominions; and ſo they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101686:15"/>2. All <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> to call home their Subjects which are in the <hi>French</hi> ſervice, and by that means his Infantry will be weak and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable: For from the ſlavery of that people, ſuch is their unfitneſs for War, that whenever they ſhall be confined to home for Souldiers, they will be conſtrained as well as contented to live in peace with their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>State</hi> to ſuffer any Levies of Men or Horſe to be made in any of their Dominions or Territories, as they have done to the great recruits of the <hi>French</hi> Armies, and to the ruine of themſelves and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To interdict all Trade and Commerce with <hi>France,</hi> is a good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient; for their Trade being obſtructed, their power at Land will ſoon become feeble and weak (the firſt giving life to the latter;) and if he ſhall lay Taxes upon his people (their Trade being taken away) it may hazard the Obedience of his Subjects, and his Souldiers will mutiny for want of Pay.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The three Eſtates General of that Kingdom muſt be re-eſtabliſhed with their Priviledges. There being <hi>fourſcore</hi> and <hi>ten thouſand</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in <hi>France,</hi> if they will draw their Swords and joyn with the honeſt Commonalty there, and with the Confederate Princes which are now in War againſt <hi>France,</hi> (which will be a generous and heroick act in them) they may deliver their own necks from that Yoke of Slavery which now oppreſſes them, and all <hi>Europe</hi> from deſtruction. For whiles the <hi>French</hi> King can exerciſe the <hi>deſpotical</hi> power over his Slaves (rather than Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects) and without controul levy what ſums of Money he pleaſes from them, they muſt never expect to enjoy their juſt Rights and Liberties, or any the <hi>Kings, Princes,</hi> or <hi>States</hi> his Neighbours, to live in Peace or Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>France</hi> muſt be oppoſed in all its endeavours for farther addition and engreatning his Dominions, eſpecially on his deſigns upon the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands;</hi> for ſhould he gain the Harbours and Ports there, he would be formidable, and an over Match for all <hi>Europe.</hi> Therefore if the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> had no Dominions in the Low-Countries, it's their intereſt, and in true policy they ought to preſerve the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> entire; and they ought to venture all their Kingdoms, and to the very laſt of their men to prevent (if it be poſſible) ſo formidable Acceſſion of <hi>Naval</hi> power to the French. After which no <hi>Plate</hi>-Fleet or <hi>Gallions</hi> could never come ſafe, nor conſequently their Monarchy ſtand much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Great Britain</hi> ought (be it ſpoken with dew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to his perſon) to have the ſame Sentiments; for if the <hi>French</hi> ſhould become Maſters of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> farewel the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Seas; farewel all Trade and Commerce of <hi>England;</hi> and his Majeſty may bid adieu to the beſt branch of his Royal Revenue, the Cuſtoms.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Great Britain</hi> ought to make himſelf <hi>Protector</hi> of the Proteſtant Kings and Princes in <hi>Europe;</hi> and the <hi>Cantons</hi> of the <hi>Switzers,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:101686:16"/>and the <hi>Griſons,</hi> are to be invited (for their ſecurity, and becauſe they can give trouble to <hi>France</hi>) into the Aſſociation: For though formerly with great reaſon (being jealous of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> becauſe of their pretentions to them) they held a good correſpondency with <hi>France,</hi> yet now it's their intereſt all to be jealous of the growing Greatneſs of the <hi>French</hi> King, and to be firm to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and to hold a true Friendſhip with them.</p>
               <p n="8">8. A firm and ſincere Friendſhip is to be eſtabliſhed between the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces:</hi> For they being the two great <hi>Naval</hi> Powers in <hi>Europe,</hi> are by Providence ſo ſeated with admirable advantages, and for the ſecurity of themſelves and of the <hi>Spaniſh Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands;</hi> that when there is a true intelligence preſerved between them, their greateſt Enemies cannot prejudice either, but they can give a check to any aſpiring Prince, and be as an invincible Bulwark againſt the ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ambitious deſignes of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>England</hi> muſt unite within it ſelf, and ſettle a kindneſs and friendſhip amongſt themſelves, (Concord or Diviſion being the life or death of a State;) for it's a <hi>Jergon</hi> of the <hi>French Cabal</hi> to diſſeminate Factions and Diviſions amongſt them, that they may not contribute their Aſſiſtance to the relief of oppreſſed <hi>Europe,</hi> or to obſtruct the deſignes of the <hi>French</hi> King for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Firebands are to be ſent into <hi>France</hi> to raiſe Diviſions amongſt them, as the <hi>French Cabal</hi> ſend their Engineers (to the diſturbance of <hi>Europe</hi>) to make a Combuſtion in other Princes Dominions, that he may with more ſafety drive on his deſignes.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Councils muſt be adapted to preſent neceſſity; and it's imprudence to expoſe ſecurity to apparent danger. In great concerns, it's not wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to reſt in the dull Counſels of what is lawful, but to proceed to quick Reſolutions of what is ſafe.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The <hi>Monarchy</hi> of <hi>France</hi> is to be <hi>cantonized</hi> into ſeveral Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, which was aimed at by the <hi>Grandees</hi> of <hi>France</hi> in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>third;</hi> and had been effected, if the ambition of <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> would have given way to it.</p>
               <p n="13">13. It's the true intereſt of <hi>Europe</hi> to oppoſe the <hi>French</hi> deſignes; and in caſe there be any occaſion of making uſe of them againſt ſome others, not to accept of their Aſſiſtance longer or further than publick Utility re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it; nor to ſuffer them to proceed after the danger is over. As it was practiſed in the Peace of <hi>Paſſaw,</hi> in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>ſecond,</hi> and that of <hi>Munſter,</hi> in both which the <hi>French</hi> were ſtopped in their full car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer by their own <hi>Allies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. All <hi>Kings, Princes,</hi> and <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Communion,</hi> to enter into mutual Leagues and Alliances, and to be incorporated into one Union; that by their joynt ſtrength they may put a ſtop to the progreſs of the <hi>French</hi> Arms. It will be prudence in them to rely upon their own ſtrength, and not to depend upon the Aids or Auxiliaries of others: 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101686:16"/>all the Councils of Catholick Princes, are governed by the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>French Penſioners.</hi> 2. The deſignes of the <hi>Conclave</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> are to extirpate out of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> the Proteſtant Religion; which they have concluded to effect by the Arms of <hi>France</hi> (that are ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly influenced by the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi>) and to re-eſtabliſh the <hi>Papacy</hi> in its ancient Glory and Splendor: for the fall of the one, is the exaltation of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 3. All Wars raiſed between <hi>Catholick Princes,</hi> are contrived to be but as <hi>Decoys</hi> to draw <hi>Heretical Princes</hi> (as they are pleaſed to call them) into Ruine and Deſtruction; and are uſed as deluſary Mediums drawn before their eyes, that they may more ſecurely advance the intereſt of the <hi>Mitre,</hi> and the deſignes of the Triple-Crown. If his <hi>Majeſty</hi> of <hi>Swedeland</hi> managed by <hi>France,</hi> his <hi>Majeſty</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> his <hi>Electoral Highneſs</hi> of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and his <hi>Highneſs</hi> of <hi>Zell,</hi> managed by the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial</hi> Court, will take the pains to ſearch to the bottom by what Artifices they have all four been engaged in War, which hath waſted their Subjects, ruined their Countries and Eſtates; they will find it was the deſignes of <hi>Rome</hi> (managed in conjunction with the <hi>Cabal</hi> of <hi>France</hi>) to bring Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and Confuſion to them all. During the late War, the <hi>Proteſtant States</hi> of the <hi>Empire</hi> have been ſo miſerably harraſſed by Winter-quarters, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, Burnings, and Contributions, that moſt of the <hi>Proteſtant Imperial</hi> Towns have been almoſt ruined, while the hereditary Countries, <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and many other of the <hi>Roman Communion</hi> in the <hi>Empire,</hi> have been ſo little oppreſſed, that they ſcarce felt it. It's a concluded <hi>Maxime</hi> of the <hi>Rota,</hi> That where there is an Enemy compounded of ſeveral and diſtinct intereſts, the beſt <hi>Medium</hi> to effect their Ruine, is to divide the Powers, and to engage one againſt the other; by that means you will bring a Conſumption to their Forces, and a Ruine to their Eſtates; and you muſt fortifie your ſelves upon their Fronteers, that when you pleaſe you may make ſudden Inroads into their Countries. With what dexterity this hath been practiſed during the late Wars in <hi>France,</hi> all <hi>Europe</hi> is very ſenſible.</p>
               <p n="15">15. To reſtore the <hi>Hugonots</hi> of <hi>France</hi> to the full exerciſe of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, according to the <hi>Edicts</hi> of <hi>Hen. 3.</hi> and <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. (which were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to them by Act of Parliament;) and for their ſecurity and the performance thereof, that they have <hi>cautionary</hi> Towns put into their hands, as they formerly had. This would be not onely an Act of Piety to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thoſe poor people from Tyranny and Slavery, but an Act of Prudence, that he could not ſafely iſſue out with his Armies to the diſturbance and undoing of his Neighbours.</p>
               <p n="16">16. The <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Great Britain, Spain, Denmark, Sweden,</hi> and the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> ought to aſſociate by Sea, and every one to ſet forth ſuch a number and <hi>Quota</hi> of their Ships as ſhall be agreed upon. If the <hi>Naval</hi> Forces of <hi>France</hi> be at Sea, they muſt be fought (except the <hi>French</hi> King be Prince of the Air, and can poſt his Ships at Sea, as he doth his Forces at Land, that they cannot be attacked, as it's ſaid, though that imagination was confuted at the Relief of <hi>Mons</hi>) if they be in <hi>Harbour,</hi> and will not take the Sea, they muſt be fired, which under the favour of a good Wind and Tyde may be effected, notwithſtanding their Caſtles and Forts.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:101686:17"/>17. To maintain Fleets conſtantly upon the Coaſts of <hi>France,</hi> is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to keep in his Ships outward bound, and to interrupt his Ships of the <hi>Indies;</hi> to meet with the Fiſhers of <hi>New-found-Land,</hi> and to ſink and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them; to forbid Strangers to bring him ſupplies of Pitch, Tar, Maſts, Munition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to burn as many of his <hi>Maritine</hi> Towns, and the Shipping in them as they can; and alſo ſuch as are not far within the Land, as ſhall be within their power; and to give leave by Letters of Reprizal to as many of the Subjects of the Confederates, as will adventure to Sea. Theſe Fleets are to be furniſhed with ſuch a number of men, as may be able to make an Invaſion into ſuch a part of <hi>France,</hi> as ſhall be thought moſt convenient to the purpoſe: So the Heads of the Parties in <hi>France</hi> muſt be conſulted, and made to part with ſuch places as ſhall be taken, till the French King ſhall be conſtrained to ſubmit to Reaſon and Juſtice.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Notwithſtanding the great noiſe the number of the <hi>French</hi> Ships make in the world, yet they may be reduced by Sea; 1. Becauſe they have no Ports in the narrow Seas. 2. None very good on this ſide the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean,</hi> ſave <hi>Brest</hi> in <hi>Britany,</hi> and the new-made <hi>Haven</hi> at <hi>Rochford</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the River of <hi>Clarent,</hi> but that is ſo deep on the Bay of <hi>Biſcay,</hi> as it's out of all <hi>Maratine</hi> courſe, except to their own Country. 3. The Ports and Harbours which they have, are ſo far diſtant from each other, that their Naval Forces may be deſtroyed by our Fleets before they can unite. Therefore nothing ought to be more the care and endeavours of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> than to keep the <hi>French</hi> King from any more Ports or Harbours than he now hath: for that Prince which hath many Ships and few Harbours, is of as little conſideration, as that Prince which hath many Ports and Harbours, but few Ships. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing multiplies Sea-men, but Foreign Commerce; and nothing ſo much that, as plenty of good Ports, Harbours, and ſafe Coaſts; (of which, to the comfort of <hi>Europe</hi> I ſpeak it, <hi>France</hi> is wanting:) but if we delay to <hi>lower</hi> the Sails of their Ambition, until they have furniſhed themſelves fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Ports and Havens, they will ſoon prove too great to be dealt withal. Therefore, I ſay, it's the true intereſt of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and of the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> and for them indiſpenſably ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, to deſtroy the <hi>French</hi> in their <hi>Naval</hi> ſtrength; <hi>New-found-Land</hi>-Fiſhery, and their <hi>Weſt India</hi> Trades, which are their Nurſery for Sea-men. By this means their Navigation being deſtroy'd, their Trade will decay, and their Power at Land ſoon diſband. No one Prince hath ſuch advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages againſt the <hi>French,</hi> as the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Great Britain</hi> hath, by reaſon of <hi>Tangier;</hi> which is ſo advantageouſly ſcituated, that it ſurveys the greateſt Thoroughfare of Trade and Commerce in the world; no Ship can paſs in or out of the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> unobſerved from thence. The <hi>French</hi> have more buſineſs in and about the <hi>Streights,</hi> and frequent the <hi>Streights</hi>-mouth with more Shipping of one ſort or other, than any two Nations in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom;</hi> from whence your Ships riding at Anchor, may weigh, or ſlip, and ſpeak with all People that paſs in or out, and may ſink or take all Ships which ſail that way; none can eſcape without a ſtrong Convoy, which will eat up all their gains; and they will think it more prudence, during a War with <hi>England,</hi> to ſuſpend their Trade, than with ſo much charge and hazard to proſecute it.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:101686:17"/>19. <hi>France</hi> being reduced in its Naval ſtrength, it will be the intereſt of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and of the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> to ſtint <hi>France</hi> for the future as to the number of Ships which he ſhall keep; as the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Italy, Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily, Grand Duke, State</hi> of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and <hi>Grand Maſter</hi> of <hi>Malta,</hi> keep by agreement ſuch a limited number of Gallies and Men of War; that one may not give occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of trouble or jealouſie to the other.</p>
               <p>Theſe Methods being obſerved, <hi>France</hi> may be compared to a man which graſps a handful of fine Sand (in hopes to keep it;) if he holds it looſe, all runs from him; if hard, but little remains; which agreeth with the <hi>Italian</hi> Proverb, <hi>Chi troppo abbraccio, poco ſtringe;</hi> He who graſpeth too much, retaineth but little.</p>
               <p>Sir, I muſt tell you again, there is no truſting to the Charity of <hi>France;</hi> Incredulity is the beſt ſinew of Wiſdom; <hi>Nihil credendo, &amp; omnia caven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, tuti crimus:</hi> And the moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King will at laſt underſtand, that it's eaſier to make Subjects than to keep them; for men may ſubmit to the force of Arms, but they will never obey but a juſt power. Preſent Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes are no Hoſtages to ſecure thoſe which receive them of a perpetual Felicity, and the moſt uninterrupted Succeſs cannot <hi>calcine</hi> an unjuſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the purity of Vertue. Cruel Empires, though they be abſolute, are not laſting. Upon uncertain moments, do the fortune of Battles and the fate of Kingdoms depend.</p>
               <p>But you were pleaſed to ſay, That I have no kindneſs for <hi>France;</hi> I do aſſure you, Sir, I have that honour and regard for <hi>France,</hi> that whereas now there is but <hi>one King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> I wiſh there were <hi>twenty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir, I am fearful I have ſtained too much Paper: I muſt with <hi>Apelles, Manum de Tabulâ;</hi> I beg your pardon for this interruption, and am,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your faithful Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
